<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A present for youth, and example for the aged, or, The remains of Damaris Pearse containing her speech after she kept her bed, and a copy of a written paper, of her own composing, which she left as her last legacy to her brothers and sisters, and was the last thing that ever she wrote : and also several pious expressions, occasionally uttered in her last sickness, worth minding : together with her funeral-sermon, preached by a reverend minister of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Pearse, Damaris, 1659-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91558</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P969C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43889</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42476277</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42476277</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151267</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91558)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151267)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2252:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A present for youth, and example for the aged, or, The remains of Damaris Pearse containing her speech after she kept her bed, and a copy of a written paper, of her own composing, which she left as her last legacy to her brothers and sisters, and was the last thing that ever she wrote : and also several pious expressions, occasionally uttered in her last sickness, worth minding : together with her funeral-sermon, preached by a reverend minister of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Pearse, Damaris, 1659-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 136 p..   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Funeral sermon, p. 83-136, has running title: A sermon preached at the funeral of D.P.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XLII, 1-2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Last words.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151267:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>Preſent for YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH,</hi> AND <hi>Example for the AGED.</hi> OR, THE REMAINS OF <hi>DAMARIS PEARSE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Containing her Speech after ſhe kept her bed.</p>
            <p>And a Copy of a Written Paper, of her own Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, which ſhe left as her laſt Lagacy to her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Siſters; and was the laſt thing that ever ſhe wrote.</p>
            <p>And alſo ſeveral pious Expreſſions, occaſionally utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in her laſt Sickneſs, worth minding.</p>
            <p>Together with her Funeral-Sermon, preached by a Reverend Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>Howbeit certain men— believed —and a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man named <hi>Damaris,</hi> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts 17.34.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>— And by it—being dead, yet ſpeaketh, <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 11.4. lat.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and Three <hi>Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi> Chappel. 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_book">
            <pb facs="tcp:151267:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151267:2"/>
            <head>To the Book.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>GO, little <hi>Book,</hi> abroad, and tell man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,</l>
               <l>What <hi>graces</hi> lodged in a <hi>Virgins</hi> mind.</l>
               <l>Declare the glorious wiſdom, power and love,</l>
               <l>Which did her <hi>infant</hi>-years to Vertue move;</l>
               <l>And fit for Heaven, when her childiſh days,</l>
               <l>Rather invited her to harmleſs plays.</l>
               <l>Urge <hi>youth</hi> to make her their <hi>Exemplar,</hi> till,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Graces</hi> ſteps they mount to <hi>Glories</hi> hill.</l>
               <l>Shame lazy Chriſtians, who are grown in years;</l>
               <l>Yet not like-working in their hearts appears.</l>
               <l>Heaven's bleſs thy errand, and make ſharp thy Words,</l>
               <l>To <hi>pierce</hi> the Sinners heart, like Spears or Swords.</l>
               <l>If they reject thee in a ſcornful heat,</l>
               <l>Tell them thou'lt meet them at Gods Judgment-Seat.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>D. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151267:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>IT is ſaid in Holy Writ, That of making many Books there is no end; which was never more verified than in this our ſcribling age.</p>
            <p>This following Collection, which is now expoſed to publick view, was not at firſt ſo intended, but collected and compoſed for private uſe, which after a while coming to the view, and paſſing thorow ſo many private hands, not only of Relations and Acquaintance, but alſo of ſome that were ſtrangers, who (all of them, as if by one conſent) earneſtly deſired it might be Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſome were reſtleſs therein; and one threatned, that if I, to whom it did moſt properly pertain to ſet it forth, did refuſe, and would not do it, it ſhould be done without me by a ſtrange hand; which indeed was the great prevailing argument that did extort it forth: for tho it diſcover weakneſs enough (as now it is); yet if it had been done by a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, in likelihood it might have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb facs="tcp:151267:3"/>ſomewhat that is worſe than weakneſs. Now you may be aſſured you have the very truth; and by what is herein contained, you have a taſt of the frame and temper of Spirit, and likewiſe of the endowments and qualifications of<note n="*" place="margin">A young woman of ſo plain education, of whom the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Collection gives you her Character, but only in a taſt: This conſidered, it was the ſoonet yeilded unto, to ſet it forth: for had it been of ſome learned Miniſter, or yet of ſome aged and experienced Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an man, it had never ſeen the light; tho the like Piety, Grace and Zeal for God, and to do good to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is not always manifeſted in ſuch.</note> a young Woman, who was ſeveral years very much afflicted with great diſtempers in her body; and lay in a torturing pain ſeveral weeks before ſhe departed; ſome very grievous ſpiritual con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flicts ſhe had, and in great Agonies: yet af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter a while, a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table deliverance, and a moſt eminent conqueſt; and tho ſhe had but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ceſſation of her bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pain, yet ſhe had moſt ſweet inward refreſhings in her Soul and Spirit, and at laſt went triumphantly to Heaven; and by ſtrength and the ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of her faith, did (as it were) trample
<pb facs="tcp:151267:4"/>upon the very neck of Satan himſelf.</p>
            <p>I am ſenſible what is here written, will not ſuit the palates of this Ages learned <hi>Rabbies;</hi> it being not calculated to pleaſe the humours of worldly wiſe men.</p>
            <p>Neither will it find eſteem among the vulgar ſort of looſe Chriſtians. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſome have ſeriouſly profeſſed they have received great benefit by it already; and who can tell, but it may benefit others? The Scripture ſaith, that out of the mouth of babes and ſucklings, the Lord hath ordained ſtrength; and God (it is ſaid), hath choſen fooliſh and weak things, to confound the wiſe, and things that are mighty; and hath choſen things that are baſe, and deſpiſed, to bring to nought things that are (highly eſteemed.)</p>
            <p>Tho the perſon that gave the occaſion hereof, was one of the weaker Sex, and but young, and of very plain and ordinary education, (only taught fine needle-work, wherein ſhe was ingenious) and little experienced in the World, and the affairs thereof; yet ſhe was ſo very a Chriſtian, ſo earneſt in taking hold of time and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity,
<pb facs="tcp:151267:4"/>helps, and means; and made ſo great proficiency in knowledg and grace, after ſhe devoted her ſelf to God; and was ſo careful to prepare for Death and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and ſo reſtleſtly longing to have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do the like, that in fine ſhe became ſo much experienced in the things of God, whereof you have ſo ample teſtimony here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after given; that I queſtion not, but her works will praiſe her in the gates, and may adminiſter occaſion unto others to bleſs and praiſe God for her, and theſe her Remains.</p>
            <p>She is gone beyond the reach of envy, and beyond our praiſes: She hath left a ſweet ſavour behind her; and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, <hi>The memory of the juſt is bleſſed.</hi> That the Lord would bleſs this unto all thoſe, into whoſe hands it ſhall come, and make it ſuccesful in doing ſome ſpiritual good to others, is and ſhall be the prayer of him, who greatly rejoyceth to be ſerviceable to Souls.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="anagram">
            <pb facs="tcp:151267:5"/>
            <head>On Mrs. <hi>Damaris Pearſe;</hi> An Anagram.</head>
            <head type="sub">Paſſe Rare Maid!</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>PAſſe</hi> on <hi>Rare Maid!</hi> unto thine home above,</l>
               <l>The World is no meet object for thy love.</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntoucht, <hi>paſs</hi> through its crowd of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; be</l>
               <l>Deaf to their charming importunity.</l>
               <l>Thine Husband's Chriſt; Eſpouſe beſides him none:</l>
               <l>Loſe not thy Nuptials, nor thy glorious Crown.</l>
               <l>When thou haſt won the point, and got ſecure,</l>
               <l>Let's know what thou enjoy'ſt, and didſt endure.</l>
               <l>That with thoſe comforts wherewith thou wert fed,</l>
               <l>Surviving friends may here be comforted.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>D. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151267:5"/>
            <head>A Preſent for Youth, and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for the Aged.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>NOT to detain the Reader with a tedious Preamble, in brief thus: The Whole of what follows, was occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Piety and Zeal of a young Woman, who may therein be an encouragement for imitation to others of her Sex; and indeed (beſides the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling of Gods Free Grace and Goodneſs towards her) that is the only deſign here aimed at: Her Name was</hi> Damaris Pearſe; <hi>ſhe was born at</hi> Dunsford <hi>in the County of</hi> Devon <hi>the 8th of</hi> October <hi>in the year</hi> 1659. <hi>She lived the most of her time in</hi> Ermington, <hi>and there departed this life the 6th of</hi> December <hi>in the year</hi> 1679. <hi>So that the whole of her temporal life, was but twenty years and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151267:6"/>a few weeks; ſhe was ſick near</hi> 4 <hi>years; and ſo weak for more than twenty weeks before ſhe kept her bed, that ſhe was not able to walk about the Chamber alone, without the help of another, and after all this, ſhe kept her bed (being in tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring pain) full ſeven weeks: The first day whereof (in the Morning) ſhe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered this following Speech,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The foregoing night had been very trouble ſome with her; ſhe having had little o no reſt, very much ſickneſs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhe had a deſire to ſee her Parents faces once more together; they being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led came forthwith into her Chamber; her Brothers and Siſters, after a little while came in likewiſe. Her Father asked her; how ſhe did?</hi> She anſwered, I have had this Night, many ſweats and colds, and have been very weak, and in much pain, but yet it hath been a very good night with me, for therein I have had many comfortable refreſhing thoughts. <hi>Her Father replyed, that in Heaven there are no ſweats or colds; no ſickneſs, or weakneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151267:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereupon ſhe began to ſpeak at firſt very ſparingly, with long ſtops, and pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, through weakneſs of body, and stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page of breath; but after a little while, ſhe ſpake wonderfully quick, and fast; faster than ordinarily when in health.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus ſhe began.</hi> When <hi>Shimei</hi> curſed <hi>Dovid,</hi> ſome that were nigh would have gone and taken off his life; but <hi>David</hi> replied, let him curſe; the Lord hath bid him. <hi>David</hi> was a great and noble perſon, and <hi>Shimei</hi> was a wicked man, and ſhould <hi>David</hi> (ſo noble a Perſon) take it ſo patiently, as to ſay, let him curſe: And I am a little piece of duſt, not ſo much as this (pointing at her ſingers end) yea not ſo much as this (holding up the utmoſt corner of a linnen cloth) yea, I am nothing, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nothing to thee, Lord! and ſhall the Lord from himſelf thus viſit me! and ſhall not I bear it patiently, that have deſerved infinitely, infinitely, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely more! Let the Lord do to me, and with me, what pleaſeth him.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:151267:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Here a little ſtop: afterward thus;</hi> My Dear Parents, you muſt not ſuffer your inferior part <hi>(meaning the Fleſh, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Carnal Affections) (as afterward ſhe expreſſed her ſelf)</hi> you muſt not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer your inferior part to riſe up and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail over the higher and ſpiritual part.</p>
            <p>You muſt not murmur or repine, whatſoever befals me: Know that there is nothing comes to paſs by Fortune or Chance: Gods will cannot be altered, or changed in the leaſt: His Will is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Juſt, and Good; and howſoever it be with me, it is according to the Good Will of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then ſhe called for ſome cordial, and her Father ſtept a little out of her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; When he was come again, ſhe thus ſpake;</hi> Have you been with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? There hath been, and there is one with the Father <hi>(meaning Jeſus Chriſt our Interceſſor, as afterward ſhe expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her ſelf)</hi> for me; and tho I am fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy duſt, yet the Goodneſs of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath followed me all the days of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151267:7"/>my life, and it is the Lords mercy that you, and I, and all others, are not conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. I ſee that his compaſſions fail not: The Lord doth not grieve, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict the Children of men willingly; and tho he afflict, yet he will not caſt off, and the Lord is breathing in more breath, to make me ready a living Soul for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>I have lived twenty years (as I take it from your ſelves) but I have been a ſinful piece of duſt, yet there is enough in him to make me white again: I am in a weak houſe, but I wait for a houſe in Heaven, whoſe Builder and Maker is God.</p>
            <p>I deſire (my dear Parents, and dear Siſters) that my words may be in ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and may take deep root in you, through the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then ſhe took a little Liquor, after which, ſhe proceeded thus:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I deſire that the words I ſpeak, may be with a ſanctified Spirit, and pure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. I have lived in the world,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151267:8"/>and have been ſo<note n="*" place="margin">Tho ſhe thus ſpeak of her ſelf, yet ſhe was a very lowly and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble maid.</note> high: I would not be contented with this, and that; but did ſtill look higher; but that was vanity: Now I ſee it is better to live in the Courts of the Lord, than in the Tents of wickedneſs, tho it were ten thouſand years.</p>
            <p>Now I deſire you, my dear Parents and Siſters; (I do not know how long I ſhall live; neither doth any man know his time; but) if you live to ſee ſuch a time, that this my weak Tabernacle lie before you, you would not be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at it, but ſay good is the will of the Lord in all his doings,</p>
            <p>I am ſorry that I ſhould beſtow ſo much of the breath that the Lord hath given me, in vain words; but there is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in Jeſus Chriſt to make it up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <p>I rejoice to ſee you my dear Parents, and Siſters, but I ſhould rejoice more to ſee you in our Fathers houſe: If we
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151267:8"/>do well here, it will be well with us in our Fathers houſe; and howſoever it be with me now, I hope it will be well with me, when this Tabernable is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</p>
            <p>I have deſired ſometimes to live in ſome Town or City; but the Lord in his Providence hindred it; and it was to fit me for his heavenly City.</p>
            <p>I am ſorry for nothing that ever I have done, but what hath not been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing to the good will of God.</p>
            <p>Concerning my being, next to God, who was the firſt Author and chief Giver thereof, I received it from you my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and I do return hearty thanks to God, and alſo to you; and as for my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo for my maintenance, I give thanks to God, and to you, unfeigned thanks.</p>
            <p>I am ſorry for the diſhonour, the great, great, great diſhonour I have done againſt the Great God; and next, for the diſhonour to you.</p>
            <p>My Siſters, I deſire you to mind the things of the eternal Spirit; if you neglect now, while here, you will loſe it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151267:9"/>for ever; and if you do not find your ſelves ſtriving againſt ſin now, you will not find the benefit hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here a little pauſe, afterward thus:</hi> This Night hath been a painful one, but yet a ſweet night to me, the ſweeteſt that ever I have enjoyed: I have had many ſweet inward refreſhings in it.</p>
            <p>I have ſometime thought to ſpeak of ſpiritual things, but could not, the fleſh hath hindred; but now I will keep the fleſh under. I have heard my Saviour ſay, you muſt not think what you ſhall ſpeak; and now I find it ſo: He (Chriſt) is my Saviour.</p>
            <p>You were talking laſt night of Mr.<note n="*" place="margin">A Godly Miniſtor who departed this life a little before this ime.</note> 
               <hi>Whiddon,</hi> and I think (as I believed) that he was a good man: I have ſome time grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and ſtranged at it, that God takes away ſuch<note n="†" place="margin">He being as to his age, in the beſt of his time.</note> men; but then I thought, as men gather their fruit: and as you that have but a little, do by your
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151267:9"/>
               <note n="†" place="margin">It being the time of Gathering in ſuch fruit.</note> apples; you gather them in for ſtore and uſe hereafter; and you take ſome delight therein, and you may do ſo; ſo the Father when he hath made his ſervants ripe, then he gathers them to himſelf for ſtore; for eternity: and he delights therein: but I am not yet ripe, but I deſire I may be fitted for his great ſtore-houſe.</p>
            <p>When I look upon my ſelf, I find my ſelf filthy, and altogether polluted; then I left my ſelf; but not hopeleſs, but gave my ſelf to God, and he took me; but I ſhould have ſaid, that God made me pure, and I polluted my ſelf; then I gave my ſelf to God, and he cleanfed me, and he will take me to himſelf, and I ſhall never be filthy more.</p>
            <p>Here we are like little children, juſt like ſo many little children, when they are out in the dirt to play, their Mother calls them to come in to be dreſt &amp; made handſome and fine, for their Fathers and Friends to look upon them, and they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151267:10"/>out of their childiſhneſs run away the further into the dirt, and will not come when called.</p>
            <p>So it is with us; our heavenly Father calls us, and we out of childiſhneſs run away from him in the Wilderneſs, to ſin and follow vanity, rather than be dreſt for Eternity, by our Heavenly Father.</p>
            <p>It is with us here, as if a Noble Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould make a feaſt, and invite ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny gueſts, and he invites them into his inner Room, his beſt Parlour; but they run away, or ſtay in ſome outer Room, in ſome filthy, naſty Place: So it is with God the Father; He makes a great Feaſt, and invites the Children of men to come; ſome come in the inner Room, into the beſt Parlour, but the moſt ſtay in the worſt Room, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out: O this is ſad! and will be ſo for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>I have heard my Saviour ſay, <hi>That wide is the gate, and broad is the way that leadeth to destruction, and many there be that go in thereat; and ſtrait is the gate, and narrow is the way which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151267:10"/>leadeth unto life, and few there be that find it.</hi> My dear Brothers and Siſters, If you live after my departure, have a care to enter in at the ſtrait gate, do not ſpend time vainly, and make fair pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and afterward be idle, and vain; be careful to pleaſe God, and his Spirit, and do not pleaſe the fleſh, that hath been too much, therefore do not pleaſe your ſelves, and miſpend time, as in looking in glaſſes, and the like, but look more into the Glaſs of the Word of God.</p>
            <p>This night hath been a comfortable night to me: <hi>Here one asked, if much ſpeaking would not do her hurt? She re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied,</hi> The Lord gives in more Strength, <hi>and proceeded thus:</hi> Improve all friends and intereſts for your ſouls good; whatſoever you do for God, it ſhall not loſe its reward; my deſires were for ſpiritual things, and ſo I deſire you my Parents, Brothers and Siſters, that your aims and ends may be for ſpiritual things.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:151267:11"/>
            <p>I have had much affliction, but the greateſt were thoſe that troubled my ſpirit. This night hath been quick, and it made me mind mortality the more; time runs away quick; we know not our own time: I believe it will be a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable time before the day of general Judgment; but we know not how near the day of our partlcnlar Judgment is; therefore ſtrive to prepare for that day. Have our Saviour rooted faſt in you. Thoſe thar are in Chriſt, ſhall be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into <hi>Abrahams, Iſaacs</hi> and <hi>Jacobs</hi> Boſoms, and be with the Twelve Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and with all other gracious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are departed: as<note n="†" place="margin">She knew, and had heard <hi>Mr. Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> preach, and had deſired him to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend her caſe to God.</note> Mr. <hi>Tho. Vincent,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Whid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and others. The hearing ſome, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the books of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, hath made me very joyful: As Mr. <hi>Joſeph Alleins,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>And you have joyed me heretofore; O that I might be an Inſtrument to give in a little comfort to you.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:151267:11"/>
            <p>Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Him that overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, will I make a pillar in the Temple of God, and he ſhall go no more out; and I will give him a new name,</hi> Rev. 3.</p>
            <p>Again, my Saviour ſaith, <hi>Rejoice, not that the ſpirits are ſubject to you; but rather rejoice that your names are written in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have cauſe to rejoice all that I can, (which is but little) that my name is writren in Heaven; for who ſo is not, ſhall be caſt out into outer darkneſs: let that be ſtampt upon your conſciences; but for me, I deſire to praiſe him that made me.</p>
            <p>Again, my Saviour faith, My Sheep hear my voice, and they follow me, and I give unto them eternal life, and none ſhall pluck them out of mine hand.</p>
            <p>I have exceedingly grieved to think how many ſhall go into the lake of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal fire, but moſtly fearing leſt any of theſe preſent ſhould; over, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and over have I grieved for them; O now think upon it while time laſts:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151267:12"/>this is a precious day; this is a good day, a day of ſalvation. It is ſaid, <hi>To him that overcometh, I will give a white ſtone, and in the stone a new name, which no man knoweth, but he that receiveth it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here ſhe hreathed a little: afterward thus:</hi> There was never a covetous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon more deſired riches, or a drunkard his cups, or a gluttonous perſon to fill his appetite, or an unclean perſon to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his luſt, or an ambitious man ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or a ſick perſon a phyſician, or a hungry man, meat, or a thirſty perſon, drink, never any that is naked, or cold, more deſired clothes, or heat, or a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful perſon ever more deſired to be comforted, or an indebted perſon more deſired a ſurety, never a weak perſon more deſired to be ſtrengthned, never any of thoſe perſons hath more deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any of thoſe things, than I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired the grace of the eternal ſpirit. None of them hath been more deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of any thing, than I have been, even with longing for Chriſt and the Graces of the Spirit. The Graces of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151267:12"/>the Spirit, are love of God, faith in Jeſus Chriſt, hatred of ſin, hungring after righteouſneſs, long-ruffering, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all theſe, and many more, I have exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly longed for.</p>
            <p>And now (my Parents) tho I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not caſt your natural bread, yer I truſt I am full of the bread of life, and ſhall be ſo for evermore. There is a fulneſs of fat things in the houſe not made with hands, in Heaven; There God and Chriſt ſit on the Throne, and the Saints ſhall; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> where too, for they ſhall judg the world. O that we would judg our ſelves now.</p>
            <p>I gave my ſelf to God; and when I have been weak, and ſick, he hath ſtrengthed me through Grace. The Lord will not be limited.</p>
            <p>If here be any that have done me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wrong or offence, (I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not) I do heartily forgive you, and all the World. I bear no enmity to any perſon or thing in the world, but againſt ſin: Whether you forgive me or not, for the wrongs I have done you, I know not;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151267:13"/>but if the eternal God forgive me, it will be well with me; and then if any ſhould kill me, I reckon no more of it than of a flea on my hand.</p>
            <p>The Lord is my portion, ſaith my ſoul, therefore will I hope and truſt in him. Bleſſed are all thoſe that truſt in him.</p>
            <p>The laſt Pſalm that ever I heard, was the fifteenth, the deſcription of a Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of <hi>Zion:</hi> And the laſt Hymn that ever I heard, was that entituled <hi>(Truſt in Gods Providence)</hi> it was very good: There it is ſaid, <hi>The righteous ſhall not be forſaken, or his ſeed beg their bread.</hi> A righteous man may have a wicked child, as <hi>David</hi> had an <hi>Abſalom;</hi> but the righteous-children of the righteous, ſhall not want their bread: The eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Spirit ſhall be their comfort. Should I live a long time in the world, I ſhould not want, for I know the Eternal God will ſupply me: The words I ſpeak, I know not in what order they are, but they are as the Spirit directs, and helps me.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151267:13"/>
            <p>The Lord is good to his ſervants, to all that truſt in him. I hope I ſhall be aſhamed of nothing, but for the works of the fleſh.</p>
            <p>The Lord is the ſame, yeſterday, to day, and for ever: He is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mega,</hi> the firſt, and the laſt, and my times are in Gods hand.</p>
            <p>My dear Father, ſo long as you truſt in the Lord, you have your reward with the Father which is in Heaven. Father you muſt be patient with your little Daughter in the fleſh. I have been in heats and colds, but the Lord is able to raiſe me up, as well as to caſt me down.</p>
            <p>I deſire when my departure is at hand, that I may lie down in peace: The Grave is a ſweet bed: I never found ſuch a ſweet bed, as that bed (the Grave) is to me, in all my life. This fleſh is laid down in diſhonour, but it ſhall be raiſed in Glory.</p>
            <p>About a year ago, I was (you know where) <hi>For certainty ſake, one asked her, ſaying, where do you mean? To which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151267:14"/>that ſtood by, ſaid, I think ſhe means at</hi> Morton, <hi>was it not?</hi> She re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, yea, it was. There I heard a good man, I believe he is ſo, he ſpake from the ſpirit, I believe he did: But when I went unto him (once and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain) hoping to receive ſome comfort from him, in private: He was to me ſtrange and filent, and his ſilence at firſt much troubled me; but ſince, I truſt my Father which is in Heaven, his mind was to teach me himſelf: (that was, by my cloſe ſtudying of good books, and earneſt prayer, thereby he would teach me himſelf) His mind, in that which I went to a man, to be reſolved in, and thereby he comforted me, and it was that himſelf might have all the Glory.</p>
            <p>My dear Brothers and Siſters, I love you ſo well, that I could give you my heart: I have many good books, and I made many<note n="*" place="margin">She privately earned ſome ſmall matter with her nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle (when able) and it was to beſtow it in books, as ſhe did every envy thereof.</note> ſhifts (that is according to the fleſh) to get them: but never wronged any perſon in the leaſt for them.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:151267:14"/>
            <p>And I have one paper, written when in much pain, which I ſhall leave with you. Think upon that, but moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly think upon the Glorious God, and upon the preciouſneſs of your own im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſouls, they are more worth than ten thouſand worlds.</p>
            <p>I have been much troubled, and I have gone to God, and have received much comfort, but never had ſo much joy and comfort in all my life, as when I was (I think) you know where: <hi>Here one asked where? To which another near her ſaid, I think ſhe meaneth, when ſhe was at Mr. <hi>Serles</hi> at the Lords Supper. Then ſhe ſaid, yea it was ſo:</hi> O the joy and comfort that I then received! It was ſuch as I never had in all my life: I cannot expreſs it: When many others ſtayed in the outer rooms and outer Courts (as hinted before) through their cowardlineſs, and childiſhneſs: with ſuch 'tis ſad: But had I breath for ever, I could not do enough for my Saviour.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:151267:15"/>
            <p>I return praiſes to the, Eternal God, for himſelf, and for my Saviour, and for the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>The Lord will ceaſe a little, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh me before I go hence, and ſhall be here no more. Tho I have but a little breath, yet the Lord can give in more: if I had none, he can raiſe me up again. The will of the Lord be done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here ſhe breathed a little, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, with an austere countenance, and her voice altered: ſhe thus proceeded:</hi> A Backſlider in heart ſhall be filled with his own ways: Backſliding is a filthy thing, but a good man ſhall be ſatisfied from within himſelf, in his heart and conſcience, by the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>God made all things at firſt, very good, but the beſt was the living Soul; but we all ſinned, and were good for nothing, but to lie with Devils; then God ſent his Son to redeem his Elect: And I truſt I am one of them, but I cannot (as yet) aſſure my ſelf; my hope is in the Lord for ever, and ever, I truſt in him, I truſt in him, I commit my ſelf
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151267:15"/>to him for ever, and ever, and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord will give in more Grace, I wait for him, and for him alone.</p>
            <p>All that I am, and all that I enjoy, is the Lords.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hitherto one wrote in ſhort-hand, but not all that ſhe ſpake,</hi>—lack abundance. <hi>Here ſhe ſtopt, whereupon the writer cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A little while after, ſhe ſpake again much more, but the pen being laid aſide, and ſhe ſpake ſo fast, and all in ſhort ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, that none thereof was written.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Next a Copy of the written Paper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forementioned, of her own compoſing, which ſhe had delivered, as her last lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to her Brothers and Siſters, whom ſhe obliged by promiſe to improve to the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and the good of their own ſouls, and was the laſt thing that ever ſhe wrote.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:151267:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>But before you have an account there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, give me leave to premiſe this requeſt to the Reader, That in reading he would mind by whom written, (viz:) that he would mind her ſex, age and education: A maid, young and plain: And likewiſe, that he would mind for whom deſigned and intended, (viz.) for her Brothers &amp; Siſters, of whom there were double the number younger, to thoſe that were elder than her ſelf; all young.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſidering this, and the intention of her affection towards them, ſo; let none nauſtate at the plainneſs of the ſtile, or phraſe, or if now and then he find repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and uſed the ſame matter, words, or Texts of Scripture, or ſomewhat borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from others. Such to whom this plain fare is beneath, may leave it: Such to whom it affords any ſavoury reliſh, let them feed on it, and improve it.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:151267:16"/>
            <head>A Copy of the laſt things writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Damaris Pearſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>O that I could but win Souls to Christ!</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 11.30.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ALL men by nature are under the power of their ſins, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5. They are naturally bent to do evil, their hearts are bent after ſin and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and it is by the convincing, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakening, and ſanctifying power of Gods Spirit, that the hearts of any are changed; And except a man be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and born again, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God, <hi>John</hi> 3.3. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.3. Except ye be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and become as little children, ye ſhall not enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            <p>And become as little children, that is, we muſt be kind, and loving one to another, and tender hearted, and we
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151267:17"/>ſhould be humble and lowly in heart; have mean and low thoughts of our ſelves; and forget injuries, and paſs by wrong done to us by others: we ſhould forgive our enemies, as we hope for forgiveneſs from God: Now we ſhould examine our own hearts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Commune with your own heart upon your bed,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.28. Whether ever there hath been a real change wrought upon your ſouls, or no? If the bent of your ſouls be after ſin, and the pleaſing of your fleſh, more than for the pleaſing of God.</p>
            <p>If your hearts be ſet upon carnal things, to gratifie ſelf, and to fulfil the luſt of your fleſh, and to love this world more than to love God; then your caſe is very ſad; but if your great care be to pleaſe God, and to eſchew evil, to avoid ſin, and to ſave your ſouls: then you are the people of God: Do you ſtudy ſo to walk, as to approve your hearts to God? is your great comfort in God? is he your portion and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? and if your greateſt comfort be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151267:17"/>in the enjoyment of God, then you are his peculiar people. It is not the forſaking of ſome ſins, that doth make the change in the heart: There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that do forſake ſome ſins, ſuch as may diſgrace them before men, but they love all ſin in their hearts; why they are as wicked as any; neither is the forſaking of ſin in time of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on onely, the changing of the heart, but the hating of all ſin; the leaſt ſin, the moſt ſecret ſin, the ſtriving againſt it, and the forſaking of it, is a ſign that there is a change wrought in the Soul.</p>
            <p>We ſhould conſider the great love of the Great Almighty God towards us poor miſerable ſinners, that when we were in a loſt condition, and could no way help our ſelves; then he ſent his beloved Son into the world to deliver us from our ſins, and to give unto us e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life. <hi>John</hi> 3.16. and we ſhould conſider the great love of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt towards us: He came down from Heaven, from the Glory of his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151267:18"/>Father, and took upon him the nature of man; he ſatisfied Gods Juſtice, in his ſuffering for our ſins, he ſuffered a moſt ſhameful, painful, and curſed death, even the death of the croſs, for ſinners, all that ſhould believe in his name. O now that people would but lay hold on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt for life and for ſalvation. He is the onely way, the truth and the life; <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.6. They that have an intereſt in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſhall have eternal life; And then as for all ſuch, if they are ſure of nothing here in this world, yet they are richer than if they had all this world to their command without him: <hi>What ſhall it profit any man if he ſhall gain the whole world, and loſe his own ſoul?</hi> Mat. 16.26.</p>
            <p>O it is the great deſire of my Soul, that people would but turn from their ſins, and give up themſelves unto the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and receive him by faith into their Souls; there was never one Soul that came unto him, and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly believed on him, that ever he caſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151267:18"/>away, but they have all eternal life, it doth grieve his heart when ſinners will not come unto him that they may have life, <hi>John</hi> 5.40.</p>
            <p>We may ſee how he was greived be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the people of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that they had out-lived the day of their viſitation, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.41, 42. And when he was come near, he beheld the City, and wept over it, ſaying, If thou hadſt known, even thou, at leaſt, in this thy day, the things that belong unto thy peace! but now they are hid from thine eyes. We ſhould take care that our hearts be not hardned through the deceitfulneſs of Sin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13. We ſhould pray to God that he would keep us from a ſeared conſcience, and from a hardened heart, and that he would make us truly ſenſible of our ſins, that we may be humbled, and that our hearts may be broken for ſin, that we may have a godly ſorrow upon our hearts ſuch as worketh repentance unto ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion never to be repented of, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:151267:19"/>
            <p>It doth greatly concern us to know whether we are of the number of thoſe that ſhall be ſaved: We know not how ſoon we ſhall dye, and depart out of this world; and if we dye without an intereſt in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, it will be miſerable with us to all eternity: we have all of us precious and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſouls within our bodies, which muſt be either ſaved or damned, muſt go either to Heaven, and be glorified with God to all eternity, or go to Hell, and be tormented with Devils to all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity.</p>
            <p>There is none can expreſs the delight and comfort that the Saints in Heaven do enjoy, they ſhall have everlaſting reſt and peace, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.2. and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al joy in the Lord, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.21. They ſhall have a kingdom, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.32. and a Crown of life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that love him, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.12. None here can tell their bleſſed ſtate, as it is written; Eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neitherr have entred into the heart of man, the things which God
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151267:19"/>hath prepared for them that love him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. They ſhall be glorified with God and Chriſt to all eternity.</p>
            <p>And then on the other way, there is none of us that doth know, nor can conceive, what it is to be damned: O what a dreadful thing damnation is; it is to be baniſhed for ever from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the glorious God, and to be tormented with Devils to all eternity, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power;</hi> It is eternal baniſhment and ſeparation from God, Chriſt, Angels, Saints, Heaven: This is the puniſhment of loſs, and the worſt of Hell, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. <hi>Then ſhall he ſay unto them on the left hand, depart from me ye curſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everlaſting fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> O terrible, terrible, to be doom'd and ſentenc'd to lie under the wrath and hatred of the inſinitely great and dreadful God for ever and ever, ſo long as God ſhall live, whoſe being is to eternity; ſo long as there
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151267:20"/>is a Devil to torment, or to be torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhall their plagues laſt.</p>
            <p>O that people would conſider, now while they are here in this world, and prepare for death: To one of theſe two places their ſouls muſt for ever be: O that the thoughts of Heaven, and the Torments of Hell, would cauſe people to conſider and prepare, that they might come ſafe to this Heaven, and eſcape this Hell.</p>
            <p>Oh it doth greatly grieve me when I do ſeriouſly think of it, of the great number of thoſe which ſhall be damned, and the ſmall company (in compariſon of them) that ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13, 14.</p>
            <p>I am a poor weak Creature, and it hath pleaſed the great God to cauſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, and weakneſs, and ſickneſs, to light on my body: Theſe two years and<note n="†" place="margin">This was written at leaſt a year and half before ſhe died; and ſhe ſickly two years and a quarter before ſhe wrote it.</note> quarter; I never having a days health in this time, but very much diſtemper and infirmity on my body.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151267:20"/>Many times I have thought that the Lord had ſent the Meſſenger of Death, to take me at that time out of this preſent life, but by his good hand my life is lengthened unto this preſent hour. Beſide all this, I have had great trouble and perplexity in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and mind, which none but God doth know of, which I could never have ſtood under, had not the Lord wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſupported me, and born me up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, by his mighty hand.</p>
            <p>Now I deſire not ſo much the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of my body; for I do think I ſhall never have the enjoyment of health more in this world: (tho it is not impoſſible with God) But if it were the Lords Will that I ſhould have health again, I do hope by his help and aſſiſtance, to improve it to his praiſe, and glory. Tho I have a ſinful and corrupt heart within me, yet the Lord is mighty to ſave, and help, and ſuccor thoſe that truſt, that put their truſt in him. Now the Will of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151267:21"/>Lord muſt be done; and I deſire that the Lord would lay no more on me, than he would enable me to bear with patience, and that he would comfort me under his afflicting hand, and that all ſin, and guilt cleaving to me, may be fully expiated, and diſcharged through the blood of Chriſt, and that the Lord would give me aſſurance of his love through Jeſus Chriſt, tho I am a ſinful creature; That I may have true and ſaving faith to lay hold on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt for Salvation, that I may never fall away from him. If the Lord ſhould leave me to my ſelf, then I ſhall periſh eternally; but I truſt in the Lord, and hope that he will pour down his rich and precious mercies on me for Jeſus Chriſts ſake, that my ſoul may be truly and perfectly ſanctified by his holy Spirit; and that I may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be lead aſide by the devices of Satan, and the corruption of my heart, and the deceitfulneſs of this world; but that my ſoul may be ſtabliſhed in righteouſneſs, and confirmed in the end,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151267:21"/>that I may be blameleſs in the day of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; that I may have a ſure intereſt in the Lord Jeſus, then I ſhall be happy to all eternity. O my deſire is, that however the Lord be pleaſed to deal with my body, that it may go well with my Soul to eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that I may have the enjoyment of God through Chriſt, for there is nothing elſe can give real comfort to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Soul. I hope that the Lord hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun a good work in me, and that he will make it perfect in the end, and that he will ſanctifie his dealings towards me, that it may be for his glory, and my eternal comfort; and I deſire that my will may be throughly reſigned up into the will of God either for life, or death; and that I may have much of Gods preſence with me, and may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways have good thoughts of him, and of his dealings towards me, in all that he doth or ſhall lay upon me, and that I may improve all his mercies for his glory, and my eternal comfort; and that when he is pleaſed to put an end
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151267:22"/>to this temporal life, that my Soul may be fitted for Spiritual and eternal life in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>O now that people would ſeriouſly think what ſhall become of their Souls, conſidering how great the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is, that go in the broad way that leadeth to deſtruction, and how few there be that enter in at the ſtrait gate that leadeth unto life, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13, 14. We have but a little time to live here in this world; and that is of very great concernment, that we ſhould make a good improvement of it; eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity doth depend upon it; as we live here, ſo it will be with us to eternity: we are now brought upon the Stage of this world, here to act our parts for a whole eternity; if we make not a wiſe choice now, we are undone for ever: What our preſent choice is, ſuch muſt our everlaſting condition be, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.42. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.25.</p>
            <p>Now is your time to repent of your ſins, and to make peace with God, it cannot be done after death; now is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151267:22"/>the time that Chriſt is offered unto you; and if you will not receive him now, you ſhall never have any part in him hereafter; now is the day of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. Now is the time you may be accepted of by God; and therefore do not ſtop the mouth of Conſcience; for if you do, it will be the greateſt Witneſs againſt you here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, then it will tare and laſh you, and be a continual torment; <hi>For their worm ſhall not die, neither ſhall their fire be quenched, Iſa</hi> 66.24. If you now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the calls of God, your conſcience will continually accuſe you hereafter; therefore have a care, do not refuſe to hearken to Gods call, for it you refuſe now, you ſhall never have any calls nor invitations from God hereafter.</p>
            <p>Have you any buſineſs, any concern of greater importance to you, than the concern of your ſouls and eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? If you are to appear before ſome earthly Judg, eſpecially if it be about a matter that concerns your life: O
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151267:23"/>how thoughtful are you to have all things ready, and in order, in reference thereunto: and ſhould not you be as thoughtful and as careful to make all ready, and to ſet all right, in order to your appearing before the Judg of all the earth? and that about a matter which concerns the life of your ſouls, about a matter of eternal life, or death? Well, what ſhall I ſay? Will you ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this great buſineſs, this great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern? Or is it all one with you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you live or die, are ſaved or dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to all eternity?</p>
            <p>Oh that people would conſider how near they are to eternity! How near we are to our everlaſting habitation! You are all going down amain the ſtream of time, into the great ocean, and you will ſhortly come thither.</p>
            <p>There is not a ſtep, you ſtep, nor a breath you draw, nor a word you ſpeak, nor a moment of time you live, but hath an influence upon eternity. Oh now that unconverted ſinners would ſet about
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151267:23"/>this great work to prepare for their ſouls and eternity, before they go hence, and be no more in this world! Sinners! will you ſet about this great buſineſs? Your work is wholly yet to do, tho it may be, your day far ſpent, your glaſs is almoſt run, your ſun near ſetting, and all your work to do.</p>
            <p>Oh 'tis high time for you to awake out of your ſleep; unleſs you mean to ſleep the ſleep of eternal death.</p>
            <p>Theſe golden ſands running, will quickly be gone; a ſhort race will ſoon be run: O what a nothing is our life! as one may ſay, a ſpan, a dream, a wind, a ſhadow, a vapour, a poſt, ſwifter than a poſt, <hi>Job</hi> 7.6. You are all go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your long and laſt home, to the houſe of eternity: <hi>Every man goeth to his long home,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.5. How doth he go? He goeth ſwiftly, always in motion, night and day, ſleeping and waking, labouring, or loitering; this poſt haſtens; time and tide ſtays not: Man doth not diſcern, or perceive how his precious time doth fly from him: And
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151267:24"/>we know not how ſoon all our precious time will be gone from us; we know not how ſoon our ſouls ſhall be ſeparated from our bodies; We know not how ſoon we ſhall paſs into eternity.</p>
            <p>And Oh that people would conſider which of the two eternities they are going towards! Oh that they would deeply and ſeriouſly conſider, that there is one place for the ſheep, and another for the goats, one place for the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and another for the ungodly; one place for believers, and another for unbelievers: An eternal night, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal day; eternal pains, or eternal pleaſure; eternal happineſs, or eternal miſery; eternal life, or eternal death; eternal Heaven, or eternal Hell.</p>
            <p>Oh that my dear Brethren and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters would truly and ſincerely ſeek after the welfare of their precious and immortal Souls, now while it is time!</p>
            <p>My dear Brethren and Siſters, I have many times had great fears and cares about your precious Souls; as you are neareſt related to me, ſo you are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151267:24"/>neareſt to my heart: I could deſire that all men would turn from their ſins and believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and cloſe with him, that ſo they may have life and ſalvation by him; but my greateſt deſire is for you, my hearts deſire and prayer to God for you, is, that you might be ſaved.</p>
            <p>My dear Brothers and Siſters, great is the miſery of an unregenerate eſtate; without regeneration, repentance, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion and holineſs, none can be ſaved, and ſee God, as in <hi>John</hi> 3.3, 5. and <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.3, 5. <hi>Except ye repent ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi> And Heb. 12.14. <hi>Without holineſs there is none ſhall ſee the Lord: and a carnale ſtate, is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of death,</hi> Rom. 8.6. <hi>And if ye live after the fleſh ye ſhall die,</hi> ver. 13. <hi>And the Apoſtle ſaith love not the world, neither the things that are in the world; for if any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him,</hi> 1 John 2.15. <hi>Know ye not that the friendſhip of the world, is enmity with God? Whoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever therefore will be a friend of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151267:25"/>world, is the enemy of God,</hi> Jam. 4.4.</p>
            <p>Now if any man be in Chriſt, he is a new creature, <hi>old things are paſt away, behold all things are become new,</hi> 2 Cor. 15.17. <hi>and as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the Sons of God,</hi> Rom. 8.14.</p>
            <p>Oh that you would conſider and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate upon theſe, and ſuch like Texts of Scripture; and try your ſelves thereby how it is with you. Mr. <hi>Joſeph Alleins</hi> book of converſion might prove a great help with the Lords aſſiſtance and bleſſing; and there are many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good books that might prove a help to you herein, which the Lord di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you unto; and that you may read and conſider, and lay it to heart; and that you would ſearch narrowly into your own hearts, and the Lord of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven grant that his heavenly and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual bleſſing may reſt upon you all.</p>
            <p>I have many times deſired the Lord for you, that he would cauſe you to ſee the great evil of ſin, and to cloſe ſavingly with Chriſt, and receive him
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151267:25"/>upon his own terms, and that you may be regenerated, and born again; that you may be truly converted unto God, that you may receive forgiveneſs of ſins, and that your ſouls may be truly ſanctified, that you may all be redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Blood of Chriſt, and may be juſtified by faith in him, and that the Lord would ſanctifie his dealings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, that it may be for his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and your good; and that you may live to the praiſe and glory of God; and be comforted in him to all eternity.</p>
            <p>Oh now that you would give up your ſelves to God, reſign up your ſelves in Covenant to him, through Jeſus Chriſt, for ever to be his, to walk in his wayes, to be guided by his laws, to be ruled and directed by him at all times, that you might never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from him.</p>
            <p>Oh, that you would truly prepare for death and eternity: Make a true preparation for death, and then you will be in a well ſet way to live; for till people are prepared for death,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151267:26"/>they are not well fit to live.</p>
            <p>Oh now you ſhould give up your ſelves to God by prayer, pray heartily to God, that he would come in with converting and ſanctifying Grace into your ſouls: <hi>Draw nigh to God, and he will draw nigh to you,</hi> Jam. 4.8 The Lord is very near to them that call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him intruth, and will never leave nor forſake ſuch as put their truſt in him. He that neglects prayer, is an unſanctified ſinner; they that neglect prayer, cannot expect the bleſſing of God, on either ſoul or body. All they that are the adopted children of God, they have the ſpirit of prayer in them; whoſoever is born of God, can in ſome meaſure expreſs himſelf to God, and cry unto him for pardon of ſin, for grace, for peace of conſcience, with earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and confidence in God, Rom. 8.15. <hi>For ye have not received the ſpirit of bondage again to fear, but ye have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the ſpirit of adoption, whereby we cry, Abba, Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:151267:26"/>
            <p>Now this ſpirit of bondage, and fear, it is the Spirit of God; there is a ſpirit of bondage once in all they that are the true people of God, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fear in them, and afterwards it doth become a ſpirit of adoption unto them. Firſt the Spirit of God doth convince people of their ſins, it ſhews them the evil of ſin, and ſo brings them in fear and bondage, about their ſins, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the Spirit of God doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort their Souls; people muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced before they be converted; they muſt be ſenſible of their ſins, and pricked to the heart, before they will ask what they muſt do to be ſaved, Act. 2.37.</p>
            <p>And then afterwards the Spirit of God doth come in with comfort to their ſouls; then the Spirit of God cauſeth them to cry Abba Father, that is, to make their requeſt to God as to a Father. Prayer is a duty that doth lie upon all people, and God doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept weak prayers from his children, if they be ſincere: There are many Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151267:27"/>that can make better prayers, (that can expreſs themſelves in prayer better) than many of Gods choſen ones, but God doth reject them, becauſe they are not ſincere, Prov. 15.8. <hi>The ſacrifice of the wicked is an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the Lord: but the prayer of the upright is his delight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We muſt pray with fervency, and with reverence and confidence: with fervency, that is, with the earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires of our hearts, crying Abba Father: with reverence, that is, we muſt reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and honour God in our hearts, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.7. And with conſidence, that is, we muſt truſt whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in God through Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. Let us draw near with a true heart, in full aſſurance of faith. <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.24. We muſt deſire the Lord that he would ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and help and aſſiſt us, to pray aright, and acceptably unto him. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. The Spirit helpeth our infirmities, for we cannot pray as we ought. It is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the light of nature, againſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for people to neglect to pray unto
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151267:27"/>the God that made them, and that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth them all their good things. If you cannot well pray of your ſelves, the Lord will help you to do it, if you be earneſt and willing; if you be ſenſible of your ſins you will not want words in confeſſion; if you be ſenſible of your wants, you will not lack expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to make them known: The Scriptures will furniſh you with expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and matter, if you read, and ſtudy, and mind them; if you can groan and cry for Chriſt and Grace, the Lord will hear and help you: We have all great need to pray to God for pardon of our ſins; for we are often defiled with ſin; and we have often need to pray to God for the pardon and purging away of our ſins, and for the ſanctifying of our Souls; and it is a great priviledge that we have a God and Father to pray un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and that will hear us when we call upon him.</p>
            <p>Now we ſhould lay aſide every weight, and the ſin which doth ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily beſet us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. Sin will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151267:28"/>beſet us, if we have not a ſpecial care to reſiſt and ſtrive againſt it.</p>
            <p>And we muſt reſolve upon ſufferings for Chriſt, if called thereunto: <hi>He that endureth to the end, the ſame ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> Mat. 24.13. All that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, muſt ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution; and tho affliction be heavy, yet it will work a far more exceeding, and eternal weight of Glory, 2 Cor. 4.17. Rev. 3.21. Joh. 16.33. Rom. 8.17, 18. <hi>If we ſuffer with him, we ſhall be glorified with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we muſt perſevere, and hold out in the ways of God, unto our lives end: we muſt be ſtedfaſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, and ever abounding in the work of the Lord, knowing that our labour is not in vain in the Lord.</p>
            <p>I would have enlarged more, but am prevented for want of<note n="*" place="margin">It being on a ſingle ſheet, thick and cloſe, written on both ſides.</note> ſpace.</p>
            <p>My dear Brothers and Siſters, I commend you to God; and to the word of his Grace, which is able to convert and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151267:28"/>build you up, and give you an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance among them that are ſanctified. Now the God of peace, that brought again from the dead our Lord Jeſus, that Great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the Blood of the everlaſting Covenant, make you perfect in every good work, to do his will, working in you that which is well pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be Glory for ever, and ever, <hi>Amen. Heb.</hi> 13.20, 21.</p>
            <p>I deſire that what I have here writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, may tend to the Glory of God, and your ſouls good and comfort.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Affectionate Siſter,</hi> Damaris Pearſe.</signed>
               <date>1678.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:151267:29"/>
            <head>Some of her expreſſions in her laſt Sickneſs.</head>
            <head type="sub">Some of the pious expreſſions of <hi>Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Pearſe</hi> occaſionally uttered after ſhe was confined to her bed; many of them ſpoken when ſhe was in ſo very great pain that it was difficult for her to ſpeak intelligibly; with ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations on them, and concerning her, worth minding.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>FOR ſome few days, after ſhe kept her bed, ſhe would often breathe out,</hi> O ſpare me a little before I go hence, and be no more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The two firſt days, ſhe had two or three extreme ſharp</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Paroxiſms.</note> 
               <hi>fits or agonies ſo ſharp that the like were never ſeen by any then preſent: She had ſome ſence of their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach; for immediately before they came, ſhe would have all in the room to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151267:29"/>pray to God for her, that, that bitter crp might paſs; and ſo again, and again, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very time: after the firſt</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Paroxiſme</note> 
               <hi>fit was past, ſhe ſaid,</hi> This is not the laſt, I ſhall have more, but none ſo bad, as that, that is paſt; <hi>and ſo it was, and theſe</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Paroxiſms</note> 
               <hi>fits on her, continued juſt ſo long, as there was (then</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">It may be Satan (the grand enemie of prayer) was permitted then more than at other times, to have ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency therein, to make diſturbance, and to ſhorten that exerciſe, and to diſſwade and diſcourage from the like afterwards.</note> 
               <hi>) praying for her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And in regard ſhe uſed one phraſe every time, ſhe would have others pray for her; which was, that that bitter cup might paſs; one that stood by, asked her, what ſhe meant thereby; ſhe replied,</hi> The Cup of Gods Wrath, <hi>which in that agony, ſhe appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and felt in her Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And a few days after, ſhe again decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that it was not to be expreſſed, what therein ſhe ſuffered, that ſhe felt the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151267:30"/>wrath of God; but even therein the Lord (ſaid ſhe) upheld me; and ſince hath given me a Proſpest, and a view of the Glory of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſome time after ſhe kept her bed; ſpeaking of the many experiences that ſhe had had; ſometimes, how ſad it had been with her when under apprehenſion of Gods diſpleaſure for ſin; but within a ſhort while after, God did refreſh and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her, even with unſpeakeable joy; but never ſo much at any one time, as ſince confined to her bed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>She would often adviſe thoſe that viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her, and thoſe that watcht by her, in their health to mind their latter end, and to prapare for it, and eternity; which they were (as ſhe ſaid) haſtning and nigh unto; and ſent ſuch meſſages to ſome others that had enquired for her; whom ſhe had not ſeen a long time; as by a near</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">M. C.</note> 
               <hi>Relation, to thoſe at her home;</hi> go <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> tell all the wicked ones in your houſe, that they prepared for a long eternity, <hi>often repeating it, and chargingher ſo to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:151267:30"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The like ſhe charged another</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">I. P.</note> 
               <hi>neighbour then preſent to tell a near</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">V. T. P.</note> 
               <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and his Family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the ſame charge <hi>ſhe gave a</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">M. W.</note> 
               <hi>third, to tell another</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">V. I. W.</note> 
               <hi>Relation and his family; yea ſhe charged all (almoſt) that came into her preſence to mind eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and to keep good conſciences, and to conſider how time was hastning away making improvement of every thing ſhe ſaw or heard, and deſired others to do the like, and all to ſtir up to prepare for eternity. She would be ſpeaking either ſome ſentence of Scripture, or ſome other good words, that were very ſuitable to ſuch as were preſent, or ſuitable to what was mentioned occaſionally in her hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; urging to do good, to repent and to prepare for death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To one that is a rich Heireſs, ſhe ſpake ſomewhat long unto: Thus;</hi> Thoſe that are rich <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> have a great privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg for the advantage of ther Souls,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151267:31"/>and to do good, before others that are poor: but yet <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> the pooreſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that is, tho he have not clothes to his back, if he have Grace, is in a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times better condition, than the richeſt man that lives; for God hath choſen the poor of this world, rich in faith, Heirs of the Kingdom; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you know that the rich man (in the Goſpel) when his goods increaſed, he inlarged his barns, and he thought he had laid up for many years; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon bid his Soul take its eaſe, ſaying, <hi>eat, drink, and be merry;</hi> but God ſaid unto him, <hi>Thou fool, This night thy Soul ſhall be required of thee;</hi> then whoſe ſhall theſe things be which thou haſt provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? He thought himſelf rich, but God accounted him a miſerable fool.</p>
            <p>O that ſuch would remember what Chriſt ſaid, when he beheld <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and wept over it, <hi>O that thou hadſt known, even thou, at least in this day, the things which belong unto thy peace!</hi> O that ſuch would mind this, before peace be hid from their eyes! For then
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151267:31"/>it will be ſad with them, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their riches; <hi>with much more, ſpoken then to the like purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">F. P.</note> 
               <hi>one that viſited her; at her farewell, ſhe ſpake thus,</hi> Remember you muſt ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear before the Great Judge of all the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Once when ſeveral young</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">I and V. A and T. O and I. VV</note> 
               <hi>folk (that were related) viſited her: After ſome little diſcourſe, ſhe held up her arm, (which was then very lean and ſmall, her fleſh being much waſted:)</hi> This <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> was once full and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous; look upon it, and while your bones are full of marrow, and you have ſtrength, improve it for God, and prepare for eternity. <hi>Much more ſhe ſpake unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To others (ſhe ſaid) There is a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty little Text, thus ſhe often called it, before ſhe expreſt it; afterward ſhe ſaid,</hi> It is this; <hi>Take ye heed, watch and pray, for ye know not when the time is;</hi> Is it not a very good one? and will you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it?</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:151267:32"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Concerning her improving of what ſhe heard and ſaw: Once hearing a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Siſter ſent down on an errand, and bid make haſte; ſaid ſhe,</hi> Why ſo haſty with the little one? but yet remember, not ſlothful in buſineſs, fervent in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſerving the Lord: chiefly mind this latter, and yet forget not the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Another time hearing one of the little ones, in a morning, mentioning meat, and bread, O ſaid ſhe,</hi>
            </p>
            <l>The living bread is he on high,</l>
            <l>That down from Heaven came,</l>
            <l>And he ſhall live, and never die</l>
            <l>That eateth of the ſame.</l>
            <p>
               <hi>Next of her improvement of the ſhining of the Sun, and its Shadow, paſſing round the Bed-poſt, in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon on one ſide, in the afternoon on the other ſide thereof; O ſaid ſhe, look and conſider how the ſhadow, that a few hours ſince, was on that ſide the bed, now is on this ſide; it ſhould mind you how time
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151267:32"/>haſtens away; So by the motion of the Clock (altho the ſtriking weight was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off many moneths before ſhe kept her bed, ſhe not being able to bear the noiſe thereof)</hi> every motion therof <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> ſhould mind us how time paſſeth; yea every breath you draw, you have one breath leſs to draw, and one breath nearer eternity than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. O mind theſe things, and learn thereby to prepare for eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſo concerning her own ſickneſs and pain, ſome weeks after ſhe kept bed, ſhe would often ſpeak it with abundance of confidence, when in extremity of pain, that it was not for her own ſake, that ſhe was continued ſo long in ſuch torturing pain;</hi> but for your ſakes <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> to thoſe then preſent, and for the ſake of all that viſit me, and all round about that know me, or that ſhall hereafter hear of me, and of my ſickneſs, that you and they all may by me be warned to make preparation for eternity, while in your health and ſtrength, before ſickneſs and pain ſeize
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151267:33"/>on you; for then it is no ſit time or caſe to prepare for death and eternity; how unſit am I now to prepare for death and eternity, were it not done before? <hi>Of ſuch like improvements made by her, you may have more anon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Being heard often ſay,</hi> I hope in God, and I truſt in God, and the Lord is my Portion, ſaith my Soul, therefore will I hope in him; <hi>and ſometimes the ſame as in the Hymn, Thus,</hi>
            </p>
            <l>The Lords my Portion ſaith my Soul,</l>
            <l>Therefore my hopes on him ſhall roul.</l>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereupon one asked her, if ſhe knew how long ſince it was, that ſhe ſet her heart wholly to ſeek, and ſerve the Lord? There was no reply then from her, ſhe not being able to ſpeak (for ſo it was with her ſometimes, near a whole day toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) but a while after, tho with much difficulty, ſhe ſpake, ſaying,</hi> As near as I can remember, it was about four years and half ſince that I really and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily in a ſolemn Covenant gave my
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151267:33"/>ſelf to God, and about three quarters of a year afterwards, I renewed and confirmed it before many others, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Lords Supper, <hi>as ſhe after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards more fully expreſſed her ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>She would much bemoan, and lament her unſerviceableneſs to God, when ſick on her bed; after this manner,</hi> Here I lie, idle, and can do nothing for God, I cannot pray, or read, or do any thing for God, but <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> as it was ſaid to <hi>Samuel,</hi> when ſent to anoint one of <hi>Jeſſes</hi> ſons; Man looketh on the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance, but the Lord looketh on the heart; and the Lord ſaith, My Son give me thy heart: The heart the Lord requireth, and the heart the Lord accepteth, and I have given up my heart wholly to the Lord, and to him onely, and the Lord hath accepted of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concerning her endowments, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments, beſides her great shill in, and her ingenious dexterity, ready invention, quick diſpatch, and curious putting out of hand, the choiceſt ſort of needleworks
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151267:34"/>and most other kinds of fine works, ſuch as young women often are exerciſed in; whether with ſilk, thread, or other mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, ſo great variety, and plenty, and ſo excellently done, as is ſcarce credible of one ſo young, as when by her made, and finiſhed; and as in theſe, ſo ſhe was skilled in writing (right ſpelling) rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and of good underſtanding, and all learnt by little inſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But beſides all theſe,<note place="margin">Of her Gifts and Graces.</note> ſhe was richly endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with choice gifts, and graces, as to inſtance in ſome,</p>
            <p>She was endowed with an excellent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive Memory,<note place="margin">1. Of her Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> as appeared not only by the many ſcore Chapters and Pſalms, both reading and ſinging, and ſpiritual Hymns, (and other Verſes) that ſhe had read, and heard, and retained in her me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; but chiefly in this, while in health, it was for ſeveral years her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant practiſe Lords dayes to hear, but not write; and tho three miles diſtant
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151267:34"/>from where ſhe lived, and ſhe ſtill walkt it when very young, which made her weary at night, yet next day ſhe did in a very legible hand write moſt part of both Sermons, that ſhe had heard the day before, both matter, and method as delivered, of which there are great multitudes left.</p>
            <p>From this ſtore houſe of her Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, as ſtrength permitted, and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was offered, ſhe ſpake many choice ſentences of Scripture, and now and then, a verſe or two of Pſalms, or Hymns, in which while in health, ſhe much delighted, and did even abound in; but after on her bed, not able to ſpeak, paſſing one or two at a time: She would often breathe forth this,</p>
            <l>'Farewel vain world as thou haſt been to me:</l>
            <l>'Duſt and a Shadow, thoſe I leave with thee.</l>
            <p>She likewiſe ſpake theſe following, at ſeveral times.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:151267:35"/>
            <l>'Muſe oft upon thy latter end,</l>
            <l>'The thoughts of death will make thee mend.</l>
            <l>'Account'ſt thou death a dreadful thing,</l>
            <l>'Which hath by Chriſt now loſt its ſting.</l>
            <l>'Glad are the Saints, diſſolv'd to be,</l>
            <l>'To live with Chriſt, his face to ſee.</l>
            <l>'Vanquiſhed death I wiſh were nigh,</l>
            <l>'It ends a Chriſtians miſery.</l>
            <l>'Exceeding welcome death's to me,</l>
            <l>'Death will I meet, I will not flee.</l>
            <l>'Quiet thy ſelf, thy day of death</l>
            <l>'Excels that hour thou firſt tookſt breath.</l>
            <l>'That deadly foe, laſt foe of all,</l>
            <l>'At laſt ſhall have a deadly fall.</l>
            <p>Preſently after ſhe ſpake this verſe, ſhe ſmiled, and ſaid, <q>It ſhortly ſhall be ſo with reference to me.</q> Another time thus,</p>
            <l>'Each morning brings a freſh record,</l>
            <l>'Great is thy faithfulneſs, O Lord.</l>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:151267:35"/>
            <l>'Rouze up thy ſluggiſh Soul O man,</l>
            <l>'When firſt awake thou art,</l>
            <l>'O then let God, and his concerns,</l>
            <l>'Be next unto thy heart.</l>
            <p>Great noiſe was a great diſturbance to her, which yet was her lot many times to hear, and ſuffer; and O that it might not be laid to the charge of thoſe that wilfully cauſed it: Once up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch an occaſion, ſhe ceaſed from what ſhe was ſpeaking, I ſhall omit the circumſtances, which made that which ſhe forthwith ſaid, the more ſuitable; it was thus,</p>
            <l>'He well may quake, and fear to die,</l>
            <l>'That in his filthy ſins doth lie.</l>
            <p>Once ſpeaking of the miſery of mankind by nature, and of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs of thoſe, whoſe ſin is pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſhe ſaid thus,</p>
            <l>'I do confeſs that I receiv'd</l>
            <l>'My very ſhape in ſin,</l>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:151267:36"/>
            <l>'In it my mother me conceiv'd,</l>
            <l>'And brought me forth therein.</l>
            <l>'O bleſſed is the man to whom</l>
            <l>'Are freely pardoned,</l>
            <l>'All the tranſgreſſions he hath done,</l>
            <l>'Whoſe Sin is covered.</l>
            <p>To ſome that ſtood by, ſhe ſaid,</p>
            <l>'Think upon God, and thy poor ſoul,</l>
            <l>'And Chriſts appearance, when</l>
            <l>'The Graves muſt open, dead muſt riſe,</l>
            <l>'And whoſe ſhalt thou be then?</l>
            <p>Yea to every word ſhe heard, or action ſhe ſaw, ſhe would have either a verſe or ſentence of Scripture ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Once being troubled at the idle talk of one preſent, that after many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts would not deſiſt; ſhe thus ſaid, He that being often reproved, hardneth his heart, ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed, and that without remedy.</p>
            <p>Another time, when a perſon of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity viſited her, her head-clothes not having been righted for ſome time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151267:36"/>of her weakneſs, ſome of her hair was come out, whereupon as ſhe was able with her hand, ſhe ſaid it aſide, but (ſaid ſhe) God hath not reſpect to the outward dreſs, and adorning, but to that which is on the hidden man of the heart.</p>
            <p>She had great Zeal for God,<note place="margin">Of her hatred of ſin.</note> and hatred againſt ſin, as appeared by ſeveral expreſſions.</p>
            <p>One time hearing a little ſiſter cry out, (O Lord) ſhe was exceedingly grieved that Gods name was taken in vain. Another time the binder of her Iſſue being looſed on a Lords day eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; aſſoon as it was known, one that was with her, righted and new bound it, but was longer about it than ſhe was willing, whereupon ſhe was much troubled, that being ſo near e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terniey, any part of the<note n="†" place="margin">* Not that ſhe was againſt the works of mercy on the Lords day, but ſhe then apprehended her ſelf at the very point of her depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and did ſo wholly fix her thoughts on God and Chriſt, that ſhe wouldnvt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in be interrupteed; yet ſhe a little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived again, and lived a few weehs afterward.</note> Lords day (tho it was then almoſt gone) ſhould be ſpent about her fleſh; and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151267:37"/>(ſaid ſhe) I repent it heartily, and do you pray that God would pardon it.</p>
            <p>She would often beg of her ſiſters, and moſtly of her that moſt attended her, to take heed of ſin, and of evil company, and would have her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe no more to keep company with ſuch an one (naming one) for (ſaid ſhe) ſhe hath been, and I fear yet is exceedingly wicked; therefore beware of her company: And likewiſe take heed of ſome others that you know, for as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, Grievous wolves ſhall enter in among you, not ſparing the ſtock; ſo now of and from among your ſelves, (that is of thoſe that are near you) ſhall ſome ariſe, ſpeaking per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe things, to draw away others after them: therefore watch.</p>
            <p>Another time hearing of ſome great diſorder of others; and indeed it was
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151267:37"/>ſo bad, as is not fit to be mentioned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians: O (ſaid ſhe) I am grieved, and troubled for them, at my very heart, becauſe of their ſin, and wickedneſs and provocation of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God; Mine eyes are ready to run down rivers of tears, becauſe men keep not thy law; but I can do them no good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At another time thus,</hi> O it grieveth, it exceedingly grieveth me to think how many ſouls will be damned, how many will be turned on the left hand among the goats, that now will not be reclaimed; but I muſt quiet my ſelf, for I am not in a capacity to help them.</p>
            <p>Before ſhe was ſick, ſhe had a great deteſtation of ſin, and would much grieve for ſuch as ſhe ſaw and heard of; but much more afterwards.</p>
            <p>Concerning her knowledg in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and in the things of God, it was much for one of her ſex, ſo young; and yet her ſelf-denial, humility, and ſelf-abaſement, was even wonderful.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:151267:38"/>
            <p>As for her know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg,<note place="margin">Of her Knowledg.</note> it is evident by what may be collected from the whole of what ſhe ſpake and wrote, that it was great, both in Scripture, and by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, not only in the letter, and text of Scripture, but alſo in the ſenſe thereof. When ſhe had any eaſe, ſhe would run over (continuing the ſpace of two or three hours together) ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Hiſtory of ſome whole book in the Bible, or ſome eminent ſtory or tranſaction contained therein, and hint at ſome notable obſervations by the way: Once ſhe talked. long concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> bondage in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and miraculous deliverance from thence, and their paſſage thorow the Red-Sea, and preſervation, and ſupportment in the wilderneſs, and ſafe conduct into <hi>Canaan:</hi> As ſhe proceeded, beſides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hints, ſhe made ſome obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on <hi>Aarons</hi> making the <hi>Molten Calf,</hi> both condemning the ſin, and likewiſe ſhewing how people now living ſhould improve it, that it ſhould teach all to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151267:38"/>be watchful againſt ſin, not only infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, but alſo thoſe in high place and dignity: Conſidering what <hi>Aaron</hi> was, and yet how grievouſly he ſinned: Likewiſe ſhe then ſpake ſeveral things concerning <hi>Moſes</hi> his Zeal for God, his indignation againſt their ſin, in his breaking the Tables of Stone, tho the Law was newly engraven thereon by God himſelf, and in his burning and breaking the <hi>Calf</hi> which they had made, and likewiſe ſhe ſpake concerning his earneſt interceſſion and requeſt to God for the people.</p>
            <p>Sometimes ſhe ran over ſome of the Pſalms, and ſaid ſuch a Pſalm or ſuch a Text (laſt night) was much in her thoughts, and that ſhe could rehearſe much of her meditation thereon; but (ſaid ſhe) 'I want ſtrength to ſpeak. One morning ſhe inſtanced in the 73. Pſalm, and gave an account of moſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in it, with ſome ſhort hints on ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of them, with reference moſtly to her ſelf, concerning her ſickneſs and her reſting and truſting in God, and wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:151267:39"/>
            <p>Sometimes ſhe would ſpeak, either on ſome grace or other, or on ſome point or head in Divinity; as once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Love of God, breaking out into admiration thereof, even of Gods love to makind in general, as in Gods ſparing, and forbearing them, in and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo much ſinning and provocation, and in Gods bounty towards them, in affording and continuing ſuch plenty of outward bleſſings of this world, and abundantly more to ſome, to wit, the offers of Chriſt in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <q>This was <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> Gods general love, his love of good-will, as ſhe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſht and expreſt it; and herein <hi>ſaid ſhe)</hi> God is wonderful, and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but admire it: But then as for Gods love of delight, that is only in and through Chriſt, to his Elect. O <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> I cannot ſpeak or think thereof, but with raviſhing admiration, ſaying, it was an infinite, inexpreſſible matchleſs love.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:151267:39"/>
            <p>Indeed all that was done or ſpoken by her, did manifeſt her great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg.</p>
            <p>Then concerning her Humility,<note place="margin">Of her Humility.</note> and ſelf-abaſement, ſhe would be much, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſpeaking (both while on her legs, and after ſhe kept her bed) what a poor worm, and what a little clod of duſt ſhe was, and that ſhe was vile, and unworthy of the leaſt mercy, leſs than nothing, yea I am nothing, nothing, nothing to the Lord.</p>
            <p>Her modeſty and baſhfulneſs made her very ſpare in ſpeaking before others (while in health) but after ſick on her bed, ſhe acknowledged it had been her fault, <q>But now <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> when my pain doth a little ceaſe, and as my breath doth continue, I ſhall not forbear to ſpeak, tho it were in the preſence of the greateſt, and the learnedſt men that are; for I am ſull, but I want ſtrength, yet had I more, I could not do enough for my God.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:151267:40"/>
            <p>Concerning ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Graces,<note place="margin">Of ſome other Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in her.</note> (to wit) her Faith, Love, Hope, Patience, and ſome others that ſhe was endowed with; it was obſervable, that theſe were in her before, but they were very remarkably increaſed and ſtrengthned after ſhe kept her bed.</p>
            <p>For,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Of her Faith.</note> firſt Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Faith, She (would often ſay (as hinted before) I truſt in God, I truſt, I truſt, (often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating it, and then add), and that is pretty much for ſuch a poor worm as I am; but it was a long while before ſhe ſpake any thing of her aſſurance, which made ſome that were often preſent, the more longing to hear ſomewhat from her of that nature: At laſt ſhe ſpake freely of her confident aſſurance of Gods love, and of her own Salvation.</p>
            <p>Whereupon one asked her, (ſaying) Have you that aſſurance? She replied with a ſtern countenance, <q>Do you think I ſpeak by rote, and at random, or that I would ſay it, if it were not
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151267:40"/>ſo, and will you not believe me?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Another time being grieved that ſo many were ſinning away their Souls to deſtruction, but <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> tho there be ſo many go to Hell, yet there are many thouſands that ſhall go to Heaven notwithſtanding: Yea the multitude thereof ſhall be ſo great as no man can number; read the 7th of <hi>Revelations (ſaid ſhe)</hi> to one preſent and when ſhe heard of the many thouſands that were ſealed, and afterwards of that innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble multitude that ſtood before the Lamb in White Robes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> She with much confidence and rejoicing ſaid, <q>And I ſhall go there too, and be one of them. And this ſhall reſt in hope,</q> pointing with her finger at her fleſh.</p>
            <p>Her love was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out into a reſtleſs longing after God,<note place="margin">2d. Of her Love, and 3d. of her Hope.</note> and Chriſt, and her hope into an earneſt expectation manifeſted by ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, as proceeded from, and do teſtifie ſhe had aſſurance; as theſe and the like. Sometimes ſhe would often
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151267:41"/>breathe forth, how exceedingly ſhe did long for the General<note n="*" place="margin">The guilty cannot deſire the coming of the Judge.</note> Judgment. At other times, thus, <q>I long, I long, I exceedingly long, I cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs how much I long for the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Jeſus Chriſt.</q> And once ſhe ſaid the whole verſe of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.2. and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten would breathe out the latter part; thus, <hi>when ſhall I come and appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Her Patience was wonderful,<note place="margin">4th. Of her Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by all that were preſent in her ſickneſs: for tho there had not a day paſt for ſome years, in which ſhe ſuffered not much pain; ſhe was very ſick, and full of pain for more than twenty weeks before ſhe kept her bed; and afterwards in extremity of pain; and before ſhe died, in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance during the ſpace of more than ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven days and nights, ſhe was as if tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured upon a Rack, and her fleſh, and bones, and bowels had been torn aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as ſhe thought, and ſometime ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151267:41"/>if it were not torn? yet never an impatient word in all, but would often ſay, <q>Yet God is good, and I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved many times more, and worſe; and that the worſt thereof was not ſo bad as Hell:</q> And once in the higheſt extremity of pain, ſhe ſaid, <q>Though the Lord tare me in ſmall pieces, yet will I truſt in him. And often thus, Though I have deſerved more, yet I know it is not for mine own ſake I thus ſuffer, but that others hereby may learn in health to prepare for Death.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Her joy and rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in the Lord,<note place="margin">5th. Of her Joy.</note> was no leſs-obſervable: ſhe would ſometimes (when in much pain) ſmile, and once ſhe laughed; it being asked her, What is the matter? O <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Satan</hi> ſhall be trod underfoot ſhortly, and ſhall never more have any thing to ſay, or do againſt me: and I cannot but rejoyce at the thoughts thereof.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Her Thankfulneſs both to God, and Man,<note place="margin">6th. Of her Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs.</note> ſhe would be much in expreſſing. Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151267:42"/>thanking God for her Being, Life, and Livelihood; from whom primarily ſhe received it: but moſtly for himſelf, his Chriſt, and Grace to her. At other times thanking her Parents, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging, that next to God, ſhe derived her Being from them; ſhe thanked them alſo for her Maintenance; ſhe thanked thoſe that Watched with, and attended her. And once when a Reverend Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter viſited her, (whom ſhe often heard, and from whom ſhe ſometimes received the Lord's Supper, when able to go) though at this time very weak, and much faultered in her ſpeech; yet when ſhe ſaw him, ſhe ſtir'd up her ſelf with much difficulty, and forcing her ſelf to ſpeak, ſaid, <q>I heartily, heartily, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily thank you; and I thank God for you, for all the good I have received by your means:</q> With many other good words ſhe ſpake to him. She was reſtleſs in deſiring the Prayers of godly Miniſters and People: And if at any time ſhe felt the leaſt abatement of her pain, ſhe would forthwith ſay to thoſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151267:42"/>preſent, 'Go praiſe God for this.</p>
            <p>Her Holy Care for the Spiritual and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>good,<note place="margin">Of her Holy Care.</note> both of Relations, and others, ſhe much evidenced; Partly in her ſpeech on her bed, (of which before) and in her Written Paper, ſhe had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to her Brothers and Siſters, with a charge given by her, and taking a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe from them (they joyntly receiving it) of making improvement thereof to the Glory of God, and the good of their own Souls. And partly, in her ſuitable diſtribution of ſome choice Books that ſhe had; with the ſame charge given to, and promiſe taken from thoſe that were preſent: and ſome Books ſhe gave to others at a remote diſtance; whom ſhe will'd might have the like charge when the Books were deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them. And (ſaid ſhe) tell ſuch an one, (naming one) that I thought ſhe had had more care of her Soul be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of late, when ſhe and I were ſome days and nights in one houſe together: but then I obſerved, that which ſince hath
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151267:43"/>made me afraid of her, and have ſhed many tears in ſeeking God for her.</p>
            <p>The like ſhe ſaid ſhe had done for one of her Brothers, with hopes that God would hear her prayers for him. And partly, in her conſtant minding others to prepare for Death and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as hath ſomewhat been hinted before, and likewiſe ſeveral other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances thereof might be given.</p>
            <p>Two days before ſhe died, ſhe char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged one of her near<note n="*" place="margin">M. W.</note> Relation; and one of her Siſters that was preſent, to be witneſs, and to mind her of it, (though very badly able to ſpeak) <hi>That Chriſt came to Redeem ſinners; and to ſeek and ſave that which was loſt.</hi> Will you remember it, and believe it? <hi>and coſt your ſelf upon him, for Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> many other good words, worth obſerving were ſpoken by her.</p>
            <p>For ſome days before ſhe died, ſhe would often ſay, <q>I had wont to ſay, (ſince on my bed) O ſpare me a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before I go hence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but now I
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151267:43"/>deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt. And O when ſhall I appear before God? and yet not becauſe of my pain, but I long to know more of the affairs of the Kingdom of Heaven: for I know very little thereof while here.</q> At another time Thus: <q>O what an aſtoniſhing admiration will it be at firſt, when I come to Heaven, to be in the immediate preſence of God, and Chriſt, and of ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable company of Bleſſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and Glorified Saints!</q>
            </p>
            <p>Once ſhe ſpake ſomewhat long, what her Perſwaſion was concerning the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conforming Miniſters; which I ſhall here omit.</p>
            <p>For more than Six weeks after ſhe firſt kept her bed, ſhe took nothing within her Lips, but now and then a ſpoonful of Sack, which gave her oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion thus to ſpeak; <q>Here I take a little Wine to do me good; but wo to them that drink up whole Bowls thereof, and that follow ſtrong drink until night, till Wine inflame them.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:151267:44"/>
            <p>She would often be ſpeaking of God's Preſence with her, and admiring God's goodneſs in providing for her; ſaying, <q>I ſee God and his goodneſs every day preſent in this Room; yea, within theſe Curtains: I ſee his holy Angels here preſent (round about me) for my good; they are Miniſtring Spirits for me, and are always preſent, for God taketh care for me, and ſends them to be helpful to me, in bringing every drop of Liquor I receive; and in help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me to receive it, and in every breath I draw: O the goodneſs of the great God, in coming down to help ſuch a poor worm as I am!</q>
            </p>
            <p>On a time when ſhe had often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated a Verſe of Scripture, one that was preſent, asked whether ſhe did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, and deſire that it ſhould be Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon after her Death? <q>No <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> it matters not to me, whether there be any Preaching upon that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, or not: but my deſire is, that it may be Preach'd home here (point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards her heart) on mine, and your hearts.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:151267:44"/>
            <p>After my departure, ſaid ſhe, then ſay,
<q>
                  <l>No ſighs nor groans from her do come,</l>
                  <l>But Everlaſting Joys are in the room.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Another time thus,
<q>
                  <l>Coffin this Corpſe, and lay't in Grave,</l>
                  <l>A Glorious Riſing it ſhall have.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>She would often ſay ſome one (or part of one) of <hi>Barton</hi>'s Hymns; but moſtly, Hymn the <hi>49th.</hi> againſt love of the World; and the <hi>69th.</hi> concerning Redeeming of Time; both of the firſt <hi>Cent.</hi> Some Verſe of a Pſalm, or Hymn, or Scripture-ſentence ſhe would ſay, when able to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>About the middle of the time of her keeping Bed (having a little eaſe) one preſent was hoping ſhe might Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover again; and that ſhortly ſhe ſhould ſee her up again in that Chair, pointing to one in the Room.</p>
            <p>
               <q>O no, (ſhe replyed) I am preſſing on towards the Mark, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151267:45"/>would be a drawing back; and I would rather go on to be with Chriſt, than go back, if it were to enjoy thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Gold and Silver: therefore do not you tell me of that which will draw back, now I am ſo earneſtly preſſing on.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Once ſeeing one whom ſhe dearly affected, penſive and ſorrowful: <hi>ſaid ſhe,</hi> 
               <q>Thoſe that depart from Iniquity, ſhall undergo many Reproaches:</q> it being the very caſe of the Perſon to whom it was ſpoken.</p>
            <p>Towards the latter end of her Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſhe would often breathe forth, Saying, <q>Come Lord Jeſus, come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and O how I long to be with thee, that I may know how it is there!</q>
            </p>
            <p>And in her laſt Night, and but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while before ſhe Departed, when her Speech was almoſt gone, it was very little, and low, and could hardly be underſtood; <hi>ſhe ſaid,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>O Lord God, King of Heaven and Earth, how dearly do I love thee!
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151267:45"/>I love thee, I love thee, I love thee:</q> often repeating it; thoſe that watched, think it was more than twenty times.</p>
            <p>She gave a Solemn farewel to her Parents, Brothers, Siſters, and Friends, and Acquaintance, and to thoſe that Watched, and to ſeveral others that viſited her.</p>
            <p>Theſe were ſome, and but ſome of the Gracious Speeches uttered by her, after ſhe kept her Bed.</p>
            <p>And though there hath been this Collection thereof, (before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) yet they are not here ſet down in that order, as to time, in which they were by her ſpoken.</p>
            <p>She ſpoke them as occaſion was offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſhe able to ſpeak: but here ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them are placed under ſeveral Heads, to bring them into ſome order.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the whole, it may
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151267:46"/>be ſaid: Theſe are the fragments that remain; had there been that provident care (as injoyned in another caſe) to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up all, that nothing thereof had been loſt, the Collection would have been much greater and better: ſuch as it is, the Lord bleſs to the Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al advantage of all thoſe that ſhall peruſe it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:151267:46"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PSAL. <hi>42.1, 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>1.</hi> As the Hart panteth after the Water-Brooks, ſo panteth my Soul after thee, O God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>2.</hi> My Soul thirſteth for God for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God; when ſhall I come and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before God?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Words that I have now read unto you, were often in the mouth, and repeated by our deceaſed Friend (and now Bleſſed Saint in Heaven) in the time of her ſickneſs: And I was deſired by her dear Relation to treat on them at this time, which is the occaſion of my turning aſide from my former Subject.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:151267:47"/>
            <p>This Pſalm, as is conceived by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentators, was penned by <hi>David,</hi> (tho it hath not his inſcription upon it, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others have not) when he was dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from the Sanctuary, and publick Worſhip of God, by <hi>Abſaloms</hi> Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or which is more probable, by <hi>Sauls</hi> Perſecution, who hunted him from place to place, and purſued him as a <hi>Partridg</hi> upon the Mountains, as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf doth complain, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.20.</p>
            <p>The Title of the Pſalm is <hi>Maſchil,</hi> commending the Doctrine of the Pſalm as uſeful and neceſſary to inſtruct the Godly how to carry themſelves under his grievous croſs of baniſhment from the ordinances.</p>
            <p>In the firſt Verſe, we have <hi>Davids</hi> earneſt longing and ardent deſires after God, ſet forth by the ſimilitude of an Hart or Stag, <hi>As the Hart panteth after the Water-Brooks, ſo panieth my ſoul af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thee, O God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond Verſe here is a repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame, deſires under other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions which amount to the ſame. 'Tis
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151267:47"/>uſual with thoſe that have their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſet upon any thing in an importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate way, as the thing is in their hearts and thoughts, ſo in their mouths: Thus it was with <hi>David</hi> here, <hi>My ſoul thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for God, for the living God; when ſhall I come and appear before God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho theſe verſes may aſſord us many uſeful inſtructions if we ſhould take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad the Words in the Particulars; but becauſe I ſhall not have time to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on them, I ſhall comprehend all in this point, which is the main of the Verſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct. That the affections, and longings, and deſires of the people of God after God, are very vehement, ardent, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate:</hi> As the Hart panteth after the Water-Brooks, ſo panteth my ſoul after God, <hi>and ſo in other places, as</hi> Pſal. 84.2. My ſoul longeth, yea fainteth for the Courts of the Lord: My heart and my fleſh crieth out for the Living God, <hi>Pſal</hi> 86.4. Rejoice the ſoul of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151267:48"/>thy ſervant, for unto thee, (O Lord) do I lift up my ſoul, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.20. My ſoul breaketh for the longing that it hath unto thy judgments at all times, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.6. I ſtretch forth my hand unto thee, my ſoul thirſteth after thee, as a thirſty land, <hi>ſo the Church Iſa.</hi> 26.8. The deſire of our ſoul is to thy name. <hi>This is the temper and diſpoſition of Gods people, to long after God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the proſecution of this point, I ſhall obſerve this method, 1. To ſhew the Qualities or Conditions of theſe longings and deſires that the people of God have after God. 2. The Reaſons why their affections and deſires are ſo carried out after God. 3. Wherein they chiefly long after God, and pant to appear before him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Qualities of theſe longings in the people of God after God, are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement and earneſt: We ſay that hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thirſt, are the ſtrongeſt of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural appetites, for by them our nature
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151267:48"/>puts out all her ſtrength for preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when it is extremely ſtraitned: Thus the people of God deſire God vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently, their deſires are not flat, languid, cold wiſhes, but high, ſtrong and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent: <hi>As the Hart panteth after the Water-Brooks;</hi> Nothing can ſatisfie him but water: So Gods people are vehemently carried out after God, <hi>With my whole Heart have I ſought thee, Pſal.</hi> 119.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The deſires of the people of God after God are conſtant, which are not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away till ſatisfied, as you know thirſt is; and it muſt needs be ſo that Gods people do continually thirſt after God, becauſe they never fully enjoy God in this life: They taſt of God here, and are made partakers of ſome ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in him, and this doth the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large their ſpirits after him: The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of Gods people after God are fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſetled, conſtant, they will and do continue until they come fully to enjoy God.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:151267:49"/>
            <p n="3">3. There is an holy impatiency in theſe longings and deſires. We read <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.2, 3. that the people of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> thirſted for water, and they mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mured and ſaid to <hi>Moſes,</hi> Wherefore is this, that thou haſt brought us forth out of the land of <hi>Egypt</hi> to kill us, and our children, and our cattel with thirſt? Gods people cannot well bear the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God: They ſay as <hi>Rachel</hi> Gen. 30.1. <hi>Give me children, or elſe I die;</hi> Oh, give us thy favour, or elſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live, <hi>thy favour is life, yea better than life,</hi> Pſal. 63.3.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The deſires of Gods people after God, are accompanied with diligent endeavours: You know that in thirſt there are diligent endeavours: The man that is athirſt cries out for drink, and runs for water, Jer. 14.3. <hi>The No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles ſent their little ones to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, they came to the pits, and found no water.</hi> He that is a thirſt runs up and down, digs in one place, and tries in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, that he may find water to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh him; ſo it is with the people of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151267:49"/>God in their deſires after God: They are complaining, and acting, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring, and trying at every pit, at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very well, at every ordinance; They will pray, and hear, and read, they are at every pool, they are in every way of God, if ſo be at length they may meet with and enjoy God, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>Saith the ſpouſe, I ſought him whom my ſoul lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, I ſought him, but I found him not, I will riſe now, and go about the city in the ſtreets, and in the broad wayes: I will ſeek him whom my ſoul loveth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing to be ſpoken to, is the reaſon why the affections and deſires of Gods people are thus carried out af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God; and the reaſon is this, becauſe God hath given them wiſdom to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, and believe that their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs conſiſts in the injoyment of God: Every one hath a ſtrong propenſity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that in which he places his felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whether ſuppoſed or real: Gods people know, that it can never be well with them, till they have a right and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in God, and enjoy communion
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151267:50"/>with him: They know that God is firſt an all-ſufficient good, that can ſecure them againſt all evil, therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to ſuch things as ſhelter perſons in danger, as to a ſheild, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1. Wall of fire, <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.5. And that he can fill them with all good, being the God of all grace, and in whom are all the treaſures of Heaven and Earth, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely more, <hi>the God of all comfort,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.3. <hi>the God of peace, that fills with all joy,</hi> Rom. 15.13. 2. They know further, that God is a proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſuitable good: They know that nothing can give true comfort but that which hath a relation, and beareth a proportion to their ſouls, and to all the exigences of it: Now God is the only ſuitable good: He is ſuitable to all their wants and neceſſities, he is an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject every way for kind and quality ſuitable and commenſurate to all their caſes and conditions. A man that is thirſty, finds his ſtomack craving, the veins do ſuck and pull, and draw for cooling and moiſtning; now give this
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151267:50"/>perſon Company, Muſick, Silver, Gold, yet here is no ſati action, for theſe are not ſuitable to his condition, ſtill he thirſts; but give him drink, and then it is well with him; ſo it is with the ſouls of Gods people, they are full of cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings and longings, give them the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and pleaſures of the world, theſe do not abate their deſires, for theſe do not anſwer the ſouls nature, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot anſwer its neceſſities; but let them enjoy God, this is a proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable ſuitable good, and this ſatisfies, and therefore it is that Gods people do ſo long after God. 3. They know God is a permanent good, and therefore that he alone can make them happy: The ſoul can enjoy no perfection of happineſs, if it be not commenſurate to its own duration: Gods people under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this, and believe this, that God only is an indeficient, a never-failing good, a fountain that can never be drawn dry, a treaſure never to be emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, one whoſe perfections never leave himſelf, and one who never leaves any
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:151267:51"/>that ever truly injoyed him. 4. They know, that though God be never ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſuitable and ſure good, yet it is no comfort to them, unleſs they have an Intereſt in him. That which muſt make them truly happy, muſt be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in God, that they may be able to ſay with the Church, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.14. <hi>This God is our God for ever and ever.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67.6. <hi>God, even our own God, ſhall bleſs us.</hi> They know that this Pronoun <hi>our</hi> is as much worth to their Souls as the boundleſs God; all is wrapt up in this Propriety. <hi>Luther</hi> hath a ſaying, <hi>Much Religion lieth in Pronouns:</hi> Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all the Conſolation of Saints lyeth in this Pronoun, <hi>our</hi> God; the <hi>all</hi> of Believers depend on this; therefore it is obſervable, How <hi>David</hi> doth roul this as a lump of Sugar under his Tongue, as one loath to loſe the ſweet ſavour of it too ſoon, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.1, 2. <hi>I love thee O Lord my ſtrength. The Lord is my rock and my fortreſs, and my deliverer, my God, and my ſtrength, my buckler, the horn of my ſalvation, and my high
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:151267:51"/>tower.</hi> This Pronoun <hi>My</hi> and <hi>Our,</hi> is the door at which the King of Saints entreth into our hearts with his whole train of delights and comforts: and therefore it is, that the deſires of God's people are ſo much carried out after God. Before I ſpeak to the third Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular in my propoſed Method, I ſhall make ſome Improvement of what alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy hath been ſpoken.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. If this be the Character of God's People, thus earneſtly to long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God; Hence we may ſee the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that is between Gods People, and the Men of the world; They (as you have heard) have vehement ardent longings after God; But theſe have their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thoughts, longings, deſires after the thing of the World; Eaſe, Pleaſure, Wealth, Honours and the like: There is nothing that they deſire, and which they think worthy the purſuing of, but onely theſe things, <hi>God is not in all their thoughts,</hi> as the <hi>Pſalmist</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.4. They are thirſty for worldly things; they cry out, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Who will
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151267:52"/>ſhew us any good?</hi> The way to be rich and great in the world. Whence is this? I conceive upon a double account. 1. The men of the world know no other good than that which the world affords: It is as true, as a common ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, <hi>Ignoti nulla cupido,</hi> The good which is not known, is not deſired: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any thing raiſes the Affection, it muſt firſt touch the apprehenſion, it muſt begin there: Now the apprehenſion of the moſt are very low, and confin'd in this particular. They think there is no other happineſs than the enjoyment of theſe outward things; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they deſire, and endeavour no other. <hi>Solomon</hi> hath expreſt it well to us, ſpeaking (as it is conceived) in the perſon of an Epicure, and worldly man, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.24. <hi>There is nothing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a man, than that he ſhould eat and drink, and that he ſhould make his ſoul enjoy good in his labour;</hi> and <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Nothing better under the ſun, than to eat, drink, and be merry:</hi> Here is the heaven of a Worldly perſon; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151267:52"/>he knoweth no other, therefore he deſires no other: <hi>if thou knowect the gift of God, and who it is that ſaith to thee, Give me to drink, thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt have asked of him, and he would have given thee living water,</hi> ſaith our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to the Woman of <hi>Samaria, Joh.</hi> 4.10. Therefore ſhe did not ask for it, becauſe ſhe knew it not; and ſo it is likewiſe with all others beſides. They knew no better than Carnal things and therefore deſire no other. 2. As it proceeds from want of knowledge of God, ſo it likewiſe proceeds from want of reliſh and ſavour of the things of God: though ſome may in ſome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral confuſed manner apprehend, that the enjoyment of God is the beſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, yet they have not any Spiritual reliſh of the ſweet ſtreams of Grace that flow from him, from whence they might deſire him. They have no ſuch Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in them, as to cloſe and comply with God. The Apoſtle ſpeaking of himſelf, and all believers, ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12. <hi>We have not received the ſpirit of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151267:53"/>the World, but the ſpirit which is of God; that we might know the things that are freely given to us of God.</hi> You ſee here, it is for the Spirit of God; and this Spirit received by us, and in us, that we know the things of God, and this is oppoſite to the ſpirit of the world which ſavours onely the things of the world. This is a ſure rule, that mens deſires do partake of their diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions; look what the men themſelves are, ſuch are the deſires that iſſues from them; as our Saviour ſpeaks to the <hi>Jews, Joh.</hi> 8.23. <hi>Ye are from beneath, I am from above; ye are of this world, I am not of this world:</hi> And what doth he infer from it? even this, that therefore there were different and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary deſires in them from himſelf; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were of the World, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they minded onely Worldly Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and things from below. And ſo it is with all others beſides: they have Worldly, Earthly, Unſavoury diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in them; and therefore they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire no other things than ſuch as may
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151267:53"/>be ſuitable to them: Oh that people would bethink themſelves, and lay to heart their notorious folly in letting out their affections upon ſuch poor mean things of the world, a little airy honour, an empty pleaſure, beggarly treaſures, things of nought, Amos 6.12. <hi>A Faſhion,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.31. <hi>A Fancy,</hi> Act. 25.23. <hi>Vanities,</hi> Eccleſ. 1.2. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain periſhing things; all the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and comforts of the world, they are but as liquor in a brittle glaſs, ſoon crackt, and ſoon loſt. A Great Man (a Biſhop) once boaſted of three things that he could not loſe, his Riches, Learning, the Kings Favour; but a while after in ſeeking a bleſſing on his meat, he could not ſpeak ſence, was forced to beg relief, and before he died profeſſed he was ſure the King did care more for the worſt of his dogs than for him: Oh take off your affections from all worldly things, ſtudy God, his inſmite perfections, that he is an all-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient good, a ſuitable, permanent, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting good, and that you can never
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151267:54"/>be truly happy, till you have an intereſt in him. Oh let out your affections after him.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Of Exhortation. Conſider your ſelves, look into your ſelves, where are your deſires; which way, and to what coaſt do theſe winds of your ſouls drive you? Is it towards God, or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the world? You crave, and thirſt, and long, and deſire, ſomething there is, which you would have, and cannot be ſatisfied till you have it; now what is it? Is it the huſks of this world, or is it bread? Do you pant after the duſt of the earth, according to the Prophets Phraſe, <hi>Amos</hi> 2.7. Or with the Church, <hi>The deſire of our ſouls is to thy name, and to the remembrance of thee,</hi> Iſa. 26.8. You are hungry and thirſty, unquiet and unſatisfied, what is the matter? Do you like the dry earth, gape and cleave for ſhowers to bring forth Corn and wine? Is the voice of your hearts, Who will ſhew us any good? or is it, Lord lift up the light of thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151267:54"/>upon us? Phyſitians judg of the ſtate of their Patients bodies by their appetites; they who long for traſh, ſpeak their ſtomach foul; they who hunger afer wholſom food, are eſteemed to be in health; ſo ye may judge of the eſtate of your ſouls by your deſires, if you chiefly deſire the traſh of the world, your ſpiritual ſtate is not right: But if you can ſay with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 73.25. <hi>Whom have I in heaven but thee, and here is none upon earth that I deſire beſides thee.</hi> Bleſſed are you of the Lord, you are in a ſafe condition; but here have a care that your deſires be qualified, as I ſpake of before, that they be conſtant deſires, not occaſional deſires, as it is with ſome when at a Sermon, or in time of danger and fear of death, O then ſuch cry out, O for an intereſt in God, for a reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God; but after a while theſe deſires are off again, which argues them not to be a thirſt, which ſtill holdeth on and increaſeth; changeable deſires are falſe deſires; and look to it, that your deſires
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151267:55"/>be ardent deſires, vehement, not low, flat, weak, indifferent, as it is with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, they pray as if they prayed not, ſeek as if they ſeek not, not preſſing, not wreſtling, ſtriving with God: Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual thirſts are not lazy wiſhes, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, formal, lukewarm requeſts; there is alwayes an edg upon that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual appetite which we call thirſting, Oh I beſeech you conſider your ſelves, and know that this is your great intereſt, to have ardent, fervent deſires after God, and that you cannot be content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without an intereſt in his favour.</p>
            <p>The third thing to be ſpoken to, is, Wherein the people of God chiefly long after God, and pant to appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him: To this I ſhall ſay, They do according to the exhibitions and conveyances that God makes of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his people: Now know that God doth convey himſelf to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, 1. Here on earth in the way of his Ordinances. 2. in Heaven by the immediate communication of himſelf:
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151267:55"/>And in both theſe reſpects, they vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently deſire after God. To ſpeak to theſe two a little.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Gods people deſire God in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, thus it was with <hi>David</hi> here in this Pſalm, this was his great deſire and longing, he was debarrred of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and now he longs and thirſts after God with a great deal of vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency and intention. Now his ſoul thirſteth for God: It appears that he deſired after God in ordinances, by that which is ſaid in the 4th verſe; <hi>When I remember how I had gone with the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, I went with them to the houſe of God, with the voice of joy and praiſe, with a multitude, that kept holy day;</hi> He minds the happineſs of his former condition, I had gone with the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, I went to the houſe of God; and we may ſee what impreſſion this made upon his ſpirit; when he compar'd his former condition with his preſent, his very ſoul was grieved; ſaith he, <hi>When I remember theſe things; I pour out my ſoul in me;</hi> and this made him to
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151267:56"/>break out in theſe words, <hi>Oh, when ſhall I appear before God?</hi> and Pſal. 63.1, 2. When he was in the Wilderneſs of <hi>Judah, My ſoul thirſteth for thee, my fleſh longeth for thee, in a dry and thirſty land, where no water is, to ſee thy power and thy glory ſo as I have ſeen thee in thy ſanctuary:</hi> He deſires to be reſtored to the publick ordinances, and to his former injoyments of them; he would have <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God in his Ordinances,</hi> &amp; he would have that communion which he had formerly, ſo Pſal. 84.1, 2, <hi>How ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able are thy tabernacles, O Lord of Hoſts! My ſoul longeth, yea even fainteth for the courts of the Lord, my heart and my fleſh crïeth out for the living God,</hi> Yea, he envieth the bird, the ſparrow, and the ſwallow, who might come near the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, when he was thruſt from them, and crieth out, <hi>Bleſſed are they that dwell in the houſe of God,</hi> ver. 3, 4. <hi>and</hi> Pſal. 27.4. <hi>One thing have I deſired of the Lord, that I will ſeek after, that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the dayes of my life, to behold the beauty of the Lord, and to enquire in his Temple.</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:151267:56"/>His deſire to enjoy God in ordinances, had the chief place in his heart above all earthly deſires, and delights what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; one thing have I deſired, this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thing, <hi>that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord;</hi> ſo again, Pſal. 119.20. <hi>My ſoul breaketh for the longing it hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy judgments at all times: my ſoul breaketh</hi> — What ardent ſtrong deſires were in the heart of <hi>David</hi> after the ordinance! No queſtion but <hi>David</hi> had communion with God in prvate in his cloſet, in his own heart he was not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective of private duties, but frequent in them; a gracious ſoul carries alway a Temple with him, but this did not ſatisfie and content this holy man; no, he muſt enjoy the ordinances of God in the meetings of his people: The Reaſon why it was thus with <hi>David,</hi> and ſo with all the people of God is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ordinance are the inſtitutions of God, and in and through theſe, doth God impart himſelf to his people, and therefore they deſire here to meet God. God hath appointed them as neceſſary
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:151267:57"/>helps in the way to Heaven, and they are not able to want them, till they come to Heaven: As God fed the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> with <hi>Manna</hi> all the time they were in the Wilderneſs, till he brought them to <hi>Canaan,</hi> but when they came thither it ceaſed; ſo it is with Gods people in regard of ordinances, they are ſuch helps as God affords to them, ſo long as they are in the world, and they may not expect to ſubſiſt without them, till they come to Heaven. The exigences of Gods people are ſuch as do indeed call for them, they have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny temptations to reſiſt, many corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to ſubdue, and many graces to ſtrengthen, and much work to perform, and can they do any of theſe without helps? Without doubt they cannot: They that think to live without ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, the life of grace, they may as well think to live without meat and drink the life of nature, and they ſhall do the one, as well as the other: True it is, that God in the neceſſary want or reſtraint of publick ordinances, is able
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151267:57"/>to make it up another way, if he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; God promiſed his people, Ezek. 11.16. That tho they were caſt far off among the heathen, and ſcattered among the countries, yet he would be to them as a little ſanctuary in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, where they ſhall come: God can make a Wilderneſs, a Priſon, a ſick chamber or bed, to be a ſanctuary, if he pleaſe, by bringing to our remembrance thoſe truths which formerly we have heard, and by his own more immediate application of himſelf to us: As God can ſuſtain our natural life if he pleaſe in the want of food, as he did <hi>Moſes;</hi> ſo he can if he pleaſe ſuſtain our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual in the want of ordinances: God can ſuggeſt good thoughts, ſtir up graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and holy deſires, ſhed abroad his love in our hearts, and become all in all unto us, as in Heaven; but ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are the ordinary helps, and the powerful helps, according to that in Pſal. 63.2. <hi>That I may ſee thy power, and thy glory, as I have ſeen in the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary.</hi> There is a power in ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as to inſtance,</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:151267:58"/>
            <p n="1">1. In the preaching of the Word, 2 Cor. 10.4. <hi>The weapons of our warfare, are not carnal, but mighty through God to the caſting down of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and every high thing that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth it ſelf against the knowledg of God, and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt: The preaching of the word is powerful to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.24. To convert, Rom. 10.14. <hi>To comfort,</hi> Iſa. 66.11. Here God ſtays his people <hi>with flagons, and comforts them with apples,</hi> Cant. 2.5. It is powerful alſo for the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, and the growth of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in grace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the Ordinance of the Lords Supper there is ſtrength and efficacy to comfort, to revive, to ſeal up aſſurance, as this ſervant of God, now departed, had experience of to the wonderful comfort of her ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the ordinance of prayer, there is power from God, and a power with God; a power from him, whereby he
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151267:58"/>does enable us to perform it, and a power with him, whereby we do prevail with him, as it is ſaid of <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 32.28. compared with <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.3, 4. That he had power with God, and prevailed: the ſame hath every true <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> he hath a ſpecial power, whereby he gains upon God in his approaches to him; Oh, but what power is prayer, when there are bands of prayer, vollies of prayer; ſingle prayers are as a ſingle hair of <hi>Sampſons</hi> head there is a power in it; but conjunct prayers, are as his whole buſh of hair: When Gods people meet together, when they twiſt their prayers, and with one conſent ſtir up themſelves to take hold of God, and hang upon him, wonderful then are Gods condeſcentions to his people: All this may ſhew, why Gods people do ſo deſire after God in ordinances. To make a little improvement of this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I paſs to the next particular.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Do Gods people deſire after Ordinances, and God in ordinances;
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151267:59"/>this then meets with the practiſe of many people, who are far from ſuch deſires as theſe. As inſtance,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Such as do not lay it to heart, nor are grieved when God threatens the removal of ordinances; ſuch hath been our barrenneſs under ordinances, our lukewarmneſs, that God may juſtly remove our candleſtick, but how few are affected with this! There have been ſome that could, for the want of their Idolatries, grieve as <hi>Micah,</hi> taking on for the loſs of his God and Prieſt, Judg. 18.23, 24. <hi>Women weeping for</hi> Tammuz, Ezek. 8.14. There are that that have grieved, for the want of their merry-meeting; it is ſaid in Iſa. 24.11. <hi>There is crying for wine in the ſtreets, all joy is darkned, the mirth of the land is darkned, mirth is gone with the liquor: There are that mourn for the want of trading; 'Tis ſaid of</hi> Babylon, Rev. 18.11. <hi>The Merchants of the earth ſhall weep and mourn over her, for no man hayeth her Merchandize any more:</hi> I might inſtance in other things; and what
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:151267:59"/>no mourning for the loſs of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God? Can people be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for the want of thoſe things that gratifie only their corrupt fleſh, and not be troubled at the removal of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances which are of ſo great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and of ſo high concernment as to the everlaſting welfare of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Souls?</p>
            <p n="2">2. There are others, that though God be ſo indulgent, as to afford Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and Liberty for the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them; yet do not value it, they have no affections for theſe things. There have been ſome that have ſaid, that they are above Ordinances, and ſo what need they care whether they have them or no? But there are too too many, that are below them, and have no heart fitted to them, and therefore are not ſenſible at all of the advantage of them; they would not be at a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon or a Sacrament from one end of the year to the other, were it not example &amp; cuſtom, and the common practice put them upon it; for their parts they could
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151267:60"/>be contented to be without theſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances all their lives; theſe are far from the temper of <hi>David,</hi> and all the people of God. There are others that withdraw from the Ordinances of God, forſake the Aſſemblies of Gods people; they think they can get as much good at home, as they can to hear a faithful Miniſter; or when they joyn in the meetings of Gods people; ſuch as theſe never found the ſweetneſs and benefit of Ordinances; they are ſuch as would be wiſer than God, who hath appointed ſuch helps as theſe, and ſo by taking a prepoſterous courſe, do bring miſchief upon their own Souls; God blaſts and curſes thoſe ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, which take from his more publick Ordinances. This is like the Manna which the <hi>Iſraelits</hi> gathered unſeaſonably, it putrified and ſtank, and worms bred in it; ſo are thoſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which are performed ſingly, and ſolitarily, and unſeaſonably, when the Meetings and Aſſemblies of Gods people are neglected. There are others
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151267:60"/>who are ſoon wearied and cloyed with Ordinances; they have ſoon enough of ſuch things as theſe; inſtead of ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here with <hi>David, When ſhall we come and appear before God?</hi> they ſay, When ſhall we be gone and depart from him? like thoſe in Mal. 1.13. <hi>Ye have ſaid, what a wearineſs is it?</hi> and Amos 8.5. <hi>When will the new moon and the ſabbath be gone?</hi> There are ſome, who are never more uneaſie, than when they are at Ordinances. Oh, how many carnal perſons, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſts are there, who have only an outſide of Religion, and ſcarce ſo much, who look upon the Worſhip of God as a matter of courſe and faſhion, and ſo accordingly come to it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Let it be a word of Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; long after delight in, and bleſs God for Ordinances: It is the greateſt happineſs that we are capable of here in this life; that whiles we cannot ſee God face to face, as we ſhall one day in Heaven; yet we may now ſee him
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151267:61"/>in the glaſs of his Ordinances, in his Word, in his Sacraments, and by prayer converſe with him. That which carnal men, and worldly ſpirits, count a burden and tediouſneſs to them, let us look upon as a very high priviledg, and reckon it as our greateſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and rejoyce in it: and to quicken and inlarge our deſires, Muſe upon the excellency of Ordinances; for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency apprehended, is that which will move deſires; diſcern that theſe things are good, and good and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for us; by partaking of theſe, we ſhall get our corruptions mortified, our graces ſtrengthned, our ſpiritual decays ſupplied, more ability gained to ſerve God in our whole converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and more evidence and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Gods love in Jeſus Chriſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
            <p>And remember, when you come to Ordinances, reſolve to put hard for it, to enjoy ſuch ſenſible Communion with God in them, that you may come off in a better and more ſpiritual frame
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151267:61"/>of heart, than you came on; reſolve with the Father, <hi>Nunquam a te abſque recidam,</hi> When I come before the Lord, I will never go away without him: The reaſon why there is no more good got by ordinances, is becauſe we do not meet God in them; and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why we do not meet God, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we do not ſo earneſtly deſire and look for him; whenever therefore you appear before God in ordinances, make it your buſineſs to ſee God, to taſte of Gods, to get down ſomething of God upon your hearts, ſome impreſſions (of God) upon your ſpirits.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, Gods people do long and pant after the immediate fruition and preſence of God in Heaven: Here they enjoy God by faith, not by ſight; here in a mediate, dark and imperfect manner through providences and ordinances, as through a glaſs darkly, but there face to face we ſhall know as we are known, as the <hi>Apoſt.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12</p>
            <p>Now Gods people long after God in this way, <hi>The ſpirit and the bride, ſaith
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151267:62"/>come,</hi> Rev. 22.17. They daily pray that Gods Kingdom may come, that the number of the Elect may be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, and Chriſt may come to judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; They wait for the adoption, the redemption of the body, Rom. 8.23. <hi>They love the appearing of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.8. Heb. 9.28. <hi>They look for that bleſſed hope, and glorious appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> Tit. 2.13.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon why Gods people do long after the immediate fruition and preſence of God in heaven is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they believe, they ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly delivered from all thoſe evils that they are liable to, while they are here in this world, and that they ſhall be made perfectly bleſſed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They count upon this, they ſhall be freed, from all evils they are ſubject to in this life. As,
<list>
                  <item>1. From the evil of ſin: Oh this is the great evil that Gods people com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of with ſo much ſadneſs; here the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151267:62"/>fleſh turneth againſt the ſpirit; there ſhall be no ſuch thing hereafter, there ſhall be no blindneſs in the mind, nor perverſeneſs in the will, nor diſorder in the affections, no pride nor ſlothful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, no carnal-mindedneſs, no fleſhli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, no coldneſs and deadneſs of heart and affection, no uneven walking, no grieving the ſpirit of God, or the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of their Brethren; no unholy thought, word or action.</item>
                  <item>2. They ſhall be freed from the evil of temptation: this world is a place of ſnares, and valley of temptations; what abundance of temptations are we aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted with here continually from the Devil, the world and our corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; but there ſhall be none of theſe in heaven: In paradiſe there was a temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but none in heaven; <hi>Satans walk and rendezvous is on the earth,</hi> Job 1.7. <hi>but he never came into Heaven, ſince he was caſt out.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. From the injuries and moleſtation of evil men; no place on earth is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from moleſtation by the Devil
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:151267:63"/>and his inſtruments, but heaven is a place where ſuch ſhall never enter; there the children of wickedneſs, and ſons of violence ſhall not afflict any more; there is no <hi>Meſech,</hi> nor tents of <hi>Kedar</hi> to be complained of, nor falſe brethren, unfaithful, unſound, hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical perſons, that are ſecret enemies to truth and piety, now diſcouraging, no deſtroying company in heaven.</item>
                  <item>4. They ſhall be freed from all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions: The diviſions, and differences and diſſentions, even among the godly which this ſtate of imperfection on earth is liable to, and lamentably cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with, do create much trouble; and many diſquietments are multiplied thereby but in heaven, there is but one mind, one mouth, as there is but one truth; not ſo much as a different apprehenſion among all the thouſands and millions of Saints there.</item>
                  <item>5. They ſhall be freed from all bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ailes, pains, weakneſs, infirmities, all afflictions whatſoever; no ſin there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, no ſorrow in heaven; all tears
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151267:63"/>ſhall be wiped away, no more of theſe tears that ariſe from the various Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of this weary life; ſuch as are Wants, Straits, Loſſes, Croſſes in Name, or Eſtates, Relations, Injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; nothing but Love in Heaven, God will never knit his Brow, nor chide nor ſtrike, never hide his face there, but they ſhall live under the ſmiles of his Face, and light of his Countenance without interruption.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The people of God do believe, and hope for a perfect injoyment of all good: It is not a meer negative happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that the Saints in Heaven par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of; a not being miſerable, an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from evil; but alſo the poſitive preſence and injoyment of all good, according to that of the Pſal. 16.11. <hi>In the preſence of God is fulneſs of joy, and at his right hand there are pleaſures for evermore.</hi> Under this, are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended thoſe great and glorious things that make up and compleat the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive happineſs of the Saints. 1. As to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151267:64"/>their Souls. 2. As to their Bodies. 3. As to their Company.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to their Souls. Their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding being inlarged and widened, ſhall have a right knowledg of all things, a clear ſight and viſion of God; <hi>Now we know but in part,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 Cor. 13.12.) <hi>but then ſhall we know, even as alſo we are known.</hi> The will ſhall be perfected with an abſolute indefective holineſs, with an exact conformity to the Will of God, and perfect Freedom from all ſervitude of Sin. The affections ſhall be ſet right by an unalterable regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; there ſhall be a conſtant cleaving to God, a conſtant loving him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſatiety or wearineſs. The Soul ſhall enjoy a full imediate uninterrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Communion with God, and frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him; <hi>While we are here, we are abſent from the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. Here our comforts are in and through Ordinances, but there God will be all in all immediately, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.28.</p>
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:151267:64"/>
            <p n="2">2. As to their Bodies, There ſhall be glory upon them; they ſhall be made like the glorious body of Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. What that is, was in ſome glimpſe of it ſeen in Chriſts transfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, Matt. 17.2. <hi>His face did ſhine as the ſun, and his raiment was white as the light;</hi> that was a little glimpſe and ſpecimen of the future viſible glory of Chriſt; and the Saints ſhall be like him, they ſhall ſhine forth as the Sun, <hi>Matt.</hi> 13.43. Their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhall be indued with new and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious qualities, as incorruption, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, ſtrength and power, acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, nimbleneſs: Their Bodies ſhall be ſpiritual, not that the Body ſhall be turned into a Spirit; but the Body ſhall then live as Spirits and Angels do, without Meat, Drink, Sleep, and ſuch like bodily Supports, and ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly conformable, and obedient, and ſubſervient to the Operations of the Spirit, the ready Inſtrument of the Soul.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:151267:65"/>
            <p n="3">3. As to their Company, They ſhall be bleſſed: oh the bleſſed Company that is in the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> God, Chriſt, Angels, Saints. — And that which Crowns all, the Saints ſhall have the perpetual injoyment of all this bleſſedneſs ſecured to them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any fear of loſing it, or being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of it. The Saints ſhall never put of their glorious Robes, after they have once put them on; their State is a ſure eternal State of actual delights. Upon theſe accounts the people of God do long and pant after the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate fruition and preſence of God in Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Let us conſider our ſelves by this property; Have we deſires after God thus? Truly it is to be feared, that abundance that do live under the preaching of the Word, from whence are held forth ſuch glorious things to be conveyed by God in the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate fruition of him; do not believe, or at leaſt do not deſire the ſame, but
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:151267:65"/>they are well contented with their Portion here on Earth; like that Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of <hi>Burbon,</hi> who profeſſed that he would not give his part in <hi>Paris</hi> for his part in paradiſe. There are they that are of this mind, they would think themſelves well a paid, if there were no other Heaven, nor no change of their eſtates that they have here in this world. But I beſeech you ſee to it, that you be of another temper and diſpoſition, that ye are panting after God in Heaven. To this purpoſe practice theſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Endeavour after a ſettled and well-grounded aſſurance, that you have an intereſt in Gods ſpecial love and favour, and that you are of the number of thoſe that ſhall one day be admitted into the immediate preſence of God, that you may be able to ſay with the Apoſtle, 2 Cor. 5.1. <hi>We know, that if our earthly houſe of this taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle were diſſolved, we have a build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the heavens.</hi> Labour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151267:66"/>this, pray much for this. It is our Saviours own direction, Joh. 16.24. <hi>Ask, that your joy may be full;</hi> O ſweet conſideration, that it is the Mind and Will of Chriſt, that we ſhould ſeek for full joy and peace in believing. And take this for an evidence, that you ſhall be admitted to the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate preſence of God, if you ſeek and and enjoy Communion with God in his Ordinances; if you do behold him in the beauties of holineſs through theſe glaſſes. I ſay, this is a pledg, a beginning, and ſo an evidence of that full Communion you ſhall have with him in Heaven, and of your ſeeing him there face to face. Are your Sabbath-days, days of Communion with God? that is a ſweet evidence that you ſhall keep an everlaſting Sabbath with him in glory; but if ſtrangers to God, and profane-hearted on Sabbaths, you cannot be for Heaven.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be in an actual preparation of your ſelves for it. Spouſes and Brides that wiſh and look for their beloved,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:151267:66"/>prepare for their coming to them, and prepare for their going to them; ſo do you prepare your ſelves for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God in Heaven. To this purpoſe obſerve theſe Rules.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Labour after the mortifying and ſubduing of ſin; eſpecially your moſt beloved ſin. Your own iniquity, as <hi>David</hi> calls it, Pſal. 18.23. While that prevails, that darkens the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and efficacy of grace in the Soul, breaks the peace thereof, grieves the holy Spirit; therefore remember what the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 Joh. 3.3. <hi>He that hath this hope of ſeeing God, puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth himſelf as he is pure:</hi> Hence when the Apoſtle would raiſe up people to an heavenly frame, he calls on them to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie their ſpecial corruption, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1, 5. We find theſe joyned together, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and <hi>looking for that bleſſed hope and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious appearing of the great God, our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Tit. 2.13, 14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be looſned from the World; for while ſtaked down and fixed here, you
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151267:67"/>are unfit and unready to remove to Heaven. It is he that is a ſtranger and pilgrim on the Earth, and that dwells in Tents here; ready on a ſhort warning to pluck up ſtakes and be gone, that is a faithful ſeeker of that better country, and a traveller toward it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.9, 10, 13, 14. You cannot have two homes, nor two reſts, nor two portions; if you take up your home and reſt in the World, you are not prepared nor principled for Heaven, nor fit to go thither. Be looſning and drawing off your hearts every day from the World; expect not either a perpetual, nor yet a long abode here. Be ſenſible of the vanity and emptineſs of things here; be often thinking of, and expecting and waiting for your remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val from hence into another World.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Be finiſhing of your work, and to that end continually doing your preſent work with all your might; do what God hath appointed and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led you to; is there any work that lies upon your hand, that conſcience
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151267:67"/>tells you ſhould be done without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, as to get your ſelves ſetled in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of Gods love through Chriſt, to clear up your evidences, to get down your rebellious corruptions: or in your place, family, common-wealth, is there any ſervice to be done? foreflow it not but finiſh, diſpatch it; while our work is not done, we are not ready.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Be often thinking of your future bleſſedneſs, this will ſet an edg upon your affections; what's the reaſon that people are ſo much in love with the world? It is becauſe their minds do run out upon it; and they promiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves great matters from it, they have inlarging fancies; and therefore they have inlarged deſires anſwerable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. The ſame would alſo be with us as to heavenly matters, if our mind were more upon them, it would then make us impatient till we were in the full fruition of them.</p>
            <p>Touching the preſent occaſion, tho I know that Funeral-Panegyricks, and the promiſcuous commendation of the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151267:68"/>dead, does abundance of miſchief, for hereby the godly are juſtly grieved and offended, and the wicked hardned and heartned in their evil courſes; the miniſtry diſgraced. Yet as the death of Gods people is precious in his ſight, ſo it ſhould be glorious in the eyes of men; I could wiſh therefore that the juſt prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and true ſincerity of every child of God, were publiſhed, even by ſome Seraphical tongue, that both the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his grace might ſhine bright to poſterity, and that ſuch a fire of Zeal for imitation might be inkindled to the heaters, that they paſſing thorow the ſame courſe of holineſs, might at length be made partakers of the ſame happineſs with the Saints of God; let this be an apology for what I ſhall ſay touching this gracious perſon whoſe Funeral we now ſolemnize; as one ſaid of an honeſt man, that he was <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogus explicatus,</hi> ſo I may ſay of this our Friend deceaſed: This Sermon was exemplified in and by her; ſhe longed after God, ſhe deſired after God in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151267:68"/>when ſhe had health diligently attending on them, fruitfully partook of them; God had bleſſed her with a good memory, as appeared by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hymns, and various texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which ſhe repeated in her ſickneſs. Her cuſtom was, that tho ſhe penned nothing of the Sermons in the hearing of them, yet the next day ſhe would write them out in a very methodical way, not only the general heads, but the particulars, with the inlargements, the which I have ſeen: She deſired God in ordinances, and communion with him in the ſame; and ſhe was very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to improve ſabbaths, which is an evidence that ſhe hath now immediate communion with God in heaven, and is entred into everlaſting reſt: It plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to viſit her with pains for a long time together; and for ſome dayes before her departure, ſhe was as upon a rack, her fleſh and bones and bowels under much torture, yet exceeding pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient under the hand of God, and would ſtill ſay, Yet God is good, and tho God
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151267:69"/>break me in pieces, yet will I truſt in God: As ſhe longed for God in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; ſo likewiſe for the immediate fruition of God, which proceeded from a full aſſurance of her intereſt in him, which God was pleaſed to give in unto her; ſhe would ſay, I did hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cry out with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>O ſpare me a little before I go hence, and ſhall be no more.</hi> Oh, but now with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Christ,</hi> and often would ſhe breathe out theſe words of the Text, <hi>Oh, when ſhall I appear before God!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She was obſerved to ſmile under her pains; and being askt the reaſon of it, O ſaid ſhe, <hi>Satan</hi> ſhall be trod under foot ſhortly, and I cannot but rejoice at the thoughts of it: She gave good counſel to her brothers, and ſiſters, and to thoſe that did watch with her, to take heed of ſin, and of evil company, and that they ſhould redeem their time, and provide for a bleſſed eternity. All underſtanding, ſerious Chriſtians that were acquainted with her, could not
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:151267:69"/>but obſerve the graces of Gods ſpirit, ſparkling forth in her; and I remember one ſaid, I could give all that I have that it were thus with my children: Many other things might be added, but I ſhall ſay no more, ſhe is at reſt as to her ſoul, and as ſhe would ſay, her fleſh doth reſt in hope; and now that ſhe is at reſt, let none diſquiet her Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by any falſe reports, it is a moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenious thing: The Poet could ſay, <hi>Paſcitur in vivos liber, poſt fata quieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit,</hi> When men are living, they are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligned and reproacht, but this ceaſes when they are dead. If any ſhould be ſo wicked, let them know, that God may reckon with them here for the ſame, but aſſuredly hereafter, Jude 15. <hi>God will convince of hard ſayings:</hi> he that will not paſs by an idle word, will ſurely call to an account for bitter ſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſms, venomous taunts, and devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like reproaches.</p>
            <p>I have but two words more. 1. One to the Parents of this ſervant of God,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:151267:70"/>that they grieve not immoderately for the death of their dear relation. Oh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the evidences that ſhe gave of her intereſt in the ſpecial favour of God, of her effectual calling out of the world into the kingdom and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the bleſſed God! Graceleſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations dying with the marks of their unregeneracy upon them, do even ſcorch the hearts of their gracious ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving Relations, with the ſence of thoſe flames which they ſuffer: This is ſuppoſed by ſome, the reaſon of that lamentable ingemination of <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 18. and laſt verſe, <hi>O my Son Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom, my ſon, my ſon Abſalom, would God I had died for thee, O Abſalom, my ſon, my ſon:</hi> as if he had ſaid, <hi>Abſalom</hi> died in rebellion, I fear he is fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a worſer hand than <hi>Joab's:</hi> Oh that my death might have prevented ſo dreadful a miſcarriage: <hi>O Abſalom, would God I had died for thee:</hi> But now when your Relation gave you ſuch teſtimonies and evidences of her gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious eſtate, I may ſay as <hi>Chriſt</hi> to <hi>Mary,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151267:70"/>—Why weep ye? While you are mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on earth, ſhe is rejoicing in Heaven: while you are clothed with black, ſhe is clothed in white, even the long robes of Christs righteouſneſs,</hi> therefore do not prophane your Scripture-hope with an unſcriptural mourning, but let your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration be ſeen.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The other word is to young per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: here is an inſtance, beſides thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of others, of the frailty and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of youth; a young Woman in the flower of her age, ſhe is gone down to the grave: O you that are young then, remember your Creator in the days of your youth, as this young wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans counſel was; provide for an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py death, and a bleſſed eternity. Oh, conſecrate your firſt time to God, it may be, for any one knows, your only time, you may die and never come to old age: It is ſtoried of a youth that came to a Jewiſh Rabbi to learn him the law of God; the Rabbi asked him, what age he was; he told his age; Why, ſays he, thou art too young yet,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:151267:71"/>thou muſt ſtay eight years longer; O Sir (ſays the youth) I have gone tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the burying-place, and have ſeen little graves, as well as long, and I may be dead before I am ſo old, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pray teach me the Law of God. O Young People think of it, begin now to be religious, becauſe your youthful time may be all your time. Let me hint a few things more by way of argument.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider your youthful time is Gods time, the firſt fruits of your time is the Lords; he required the firſt fruits as his due; you rob God, if you do not give up your ſelves to him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider, your youthful time is the beſt time; now you are moſt active, vigorous, quick, as you are now more capable to underſtand any trade of life, ſo to take in the principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, if you would give your minds to it; Religion will be more facile, and eaſy to you; you are not poſſeſt with ſuch evil notions, and corrupt
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:151267:71"/>principles, as you may be if you come to age; you will then be more indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, you will be habituated in ſin, and the devil will have a ſtronger claim and intereſt in you, who will not be ſo eaſily put off; O then, mind Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on while you are young; it will be a great deal more delightful, and eaſy, and comfortable, if you begin betimes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider, this timely beginning will prevent a great deal of guilt and trouble in your ſouls; when a man in a journey ſets forth early, he goes on with comfort; but if he neglects the morning, and ſets out late, he muſt run, and ride, and that in the dark: O they that ſet forth for Religion in the morning of their time, prevent a great deal of trouble and ſin.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider, by this means you will be very deſirable, grateful, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful, acceptable to God and good men; O! to ſee an holy, humble, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſpirit in young people, to hear them ſpeak of the things of Chriſt, and find them pliable to the ways of God;
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:151267:72"/>O what a pleaſant ſight is this? What delight do ſuch to the Lord? Such have a principal ſhare of Chriſts love, who ſeek him betimes, Prov. 8.17. <hi>I love them that love me, and they that ſeek me early ſhall find me:</hi> 'Tis ſpoken by way of Emphaſis and addition, thoſe that ſeek me early ſhall be ſure to find me; the Lord takes ſpecial notice of the love of his people in their youthful time, Jer. 2.2. <hi>I remember the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thy youth;</hi> O what a lovely fight! it delights God and Saints to ſee young ſouls, humble, holy, ſerious, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury, heavenly, full of knowledg, full of zeal. O what a beauty is a young <hi>Samuel,</hi> a young <hi>Abijah,</hi> a young <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> a young <hi>Timothy?</hi> What honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable mention is made of theſe in Scripture! And it was the honour of <hi>Andronicus</hi> and <hi>Junia,</hi> that they were in Chriſt betimes, Rom. 16.7. Oh if you give up your ſelves to Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, you will be exceeding acceptable to God, and good men.</p>
            <pb n="135" facs="tcp:151267:72"/>
            <p n="5">5. Begin betimes to be religious, for hereby you will attain to a greater growth in Chriſtianity, and ſettlement in the truth and wayes of Godlineſs; you ſhall bring more glory to God, be more ſerviceable to your generation, and lay up a greater and more ſure foundation for glory; yea, the more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent and abundant you have been in grace, the greater Crown of Glory will be ſet on your head in Heaven. O now you young people, beſtir your ſelves, labour after knowledg, ſet apart time to read the Scripture and other good books, and be earneſt with God to give you an heart, to know, and an eye to ſee the excellency of Jeſus Chriſt; fly the luſts of youth, endeavour what you can to be under a faithful Miniſtry; and get into acquaintance and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with good people, and caſt off all vain company: O there is a great deal of advantage, by being in good company, they will inſtruct, counſel,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:151267:73"/>comfort, and encourage you in your courſe of godlineſs. Conſider what I have ſaid, and the Lord bleſs theſe good counſels unto you.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151267:73"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
